- User Account Control.
I mentioned User Account
Control briefly before,
but we're going to cover
it a little bit more
in depth in this lesson.
First, let me ask you, how do you
log into your computer each day?
Are you logged in as an administrator,
or are you logged in as a normal user?
For me, I log in as a normal user,
and I only go to my administrator account
when I need to do something that an
administrator would have to do.
Like, install a program, remove a program,
or something else like that.
Now, user account control, or UAC,
is a security component inside of Windows,
that keeps every user
in standard user mode,
instead of acting like administrator user.
Now, the only exception to this,
is if you're logged in as
the administrator account.
That default administrator
that's created by Windows.
For that reason, I recommend disabling the
administrator account and logging in
as a standard user each time.
Now, there are two main benefits
to using UAC, or User Account Control.
The first one, is it
eliminates unnecessary
admin level requests
for Windows resources.
If you're browsing the internet,
you probably don't need
admin level rights to do it.
And so, UAC keeps you as a user level,
until something that requires
admin level comes to play.
Number two, it's going to
reduce the risk of malware,
because it's going to
force you to be using
that user level credentials.
If you were browsing around
using admin level privileges,
this can cause system
issues, because the malware
will be running as an admin,
and you don't want that to happen.
So what does UAC look like?
Well, if you try to run a program,
or do something that requires
admin level permissions,
this box will show up, and
you simply have to click yes,
and it will let you go
and run that as an admin,
if you're an administrative user.
But normally, everything else
is going to be run as a user.
Now, some people don't like UAC,
and they want to turn it off.
Can you turn it off?
Well, yes.
You can turn off UAC by disabling
it from the control panel.
That said, I don't recommend doing that.
UAC is there for your benefit.
It's there to increase the
security of your system,
and it should be used to make sure
you're operating as a user, at all times,
except for when you
need to run as an admin.