- Now, I know that we've covered
a lot of different technologies
in this section of the course
as we discussed authentication.
So I wanted to do a quick
summarization for you.
This is a down and dirty summary
with only one to two sentences
per topic of the information we covered
and this is the stuff
that's most pertinent
and most likely to be seen on exam day.
First, 802.1x is an IEEE
standard that defines
Port-Based Network Access Control or PNAC.
802.1x is a data link layer
authentication technology
that's used to connect devices
to a wired or wireless LAN.
Also, it defines the EAP protocol.
Second, LDAP is the light weight
directory access protocol.
It's an application layer
protocol for accessing
and modifying directory services data.
Microsoft's Active Directory uses LDAP.
Third, Kerberos is an
authentication protocol
that's used in Windows to identify clients
to a server using mutual authentication.
In Windows, this in implemented
through a series of tickets.
Fourth, Remote Access Services or RAS
is a service that enables dial-up
and VPN connections to
occur from remote clients.
Next, the Challenge
Handshake Protocol or CHAP
is an authentication scheme
that's used for standard
dial-up connections.
Next, RADIUS is a centralized
administration system
for dial-up, VPN and
wireless authentication.
It's going to use 1812 and 1813
or ports 1645 and 1646
using UDP for it's transport mechanism.
RADIUS is used with 802.1x and EAP.
Finally, TACACS+.
TACACS+ is a Cisco proprietary
remote authentication system
that provides separate authentication
and authorization functions using port 49
over a TCP connection.
TACACS+ is similar to RADIUS,
but it is not considered cross platform.
Once again, this was a very short lesson.
I just wanted to cover the highlights
from this entire section of the course
to make sure that you didn't
miss any of the key points
and key takeaways that
you need for the exam.