- In this lesson, we're going
to discuss the use of RAIDS
to ensure your data redundancy.
You first learned about RAIDS
all the way back in your A plus studies.
If you remember a RAID
is a redundant array
of independent disks
which is essentially going to allow you
to combine multiple physical hard disks
into a single logical hard disk drive
inside of the operating system.
Now, for the security plus exam
you need to know about
a couple of RAID types
including; RAID 0, RAID 1,
RAID 5, RAID 6 and RAID 10.
A RAID 0 provides data
striping across multiple disks
and is used to increase your performance.
The key word here is striping.
For example, you might use a RAID 0
when you need performance,
but you don't care about
fault tolerance, so a
good example of this is
I do a lot of video editing
and so I really care about
performance there as I'm
editing these raw videos
and so by having these two
drives working together,
I can do things much quicker
than I could with a single drive.
Now to do a RAID 0, you
do need at least two disks
to work in tandem with each other.
The next one we have is a RAID 1
and this is going to provide redundancy
by mirroring the data
identically to two hard drives.
So if one drive fails,
the other can continue to operate
because it has a full copy of
everything that was on there.
This provides the least amount of downtime
because there is always
that complete copy of data
ready at a moment's notice to take over.
This provides wonderful fault tolerance,
but it can it can only be used
with two physical hard disks
and that provide you with
one single logical hard disk
inside the operating system.
A good example of this
is once I'm finished
editing all my videos
and I have the final the final product,
I want to make sure I don't lose it,
so I can actually move
that over to a RAID 1
where I get two identical
copies of that file
one on each of those drives.
Now, the next one we're going
to talk about is a RAID 5.
A RAID 5 is known as a
striping disk with parity.
It requires at least three
physical disk drives to work,
and it provides fault tolerance
by striping the data across multiple disks
and writing parity data
to the multiple disks too.
If one disk fails, the other
two can reconstruct the data
based on the parity and
they continue to operate.
This means that if one
of those drives fails,
I can pull it out,
put in a new drive
and it will rebuild itself inside the RAID
as it keeps moving and operating
for the rest of the system.
Next, we have a RAID 6
and a RAID 6 is a
modified form of a RAID 5.
In fact, it's one better than a RAID 5
that's why we call it a RAID 6.
Now, it's going to use data
striping across multiple disks
just like a RAID 5 did,
but instead of having one
stripe for parity data,
it's actually going to have
two stripes for parity data.
This requires another
disk in the array to work
so you need at least four physical disks,
but that does provide you
additional fault tolerance
because you can lose up
to two of these four disks
and the RAID will still
continue to function.
The last RAID we have
is known as a RAID 1 0
which is written as RAID 10.
This combines the advantages
of a RAID 1 and a RAID 0
because one plus zero equals 10.
This requires four physical
disks just like a RAID 6
and it's going to provide
you with a redundant mirror
of striped drives and
its fully fault tolerant.
This gives us all the speed of a RAID 0
by splitting up the load
across two sets of RAIDs,
but it also gives us the
full redundancy of a RAID 1
by having those two RAID 1 in there.
Now, this all works as
one combined logical drive
even though it uses those four drives
split up into two pairs of two.
So, when we think of RAIDs,
they can be categorized as;
failure resistant, fault-tolerant
and disaster-tolerant.
These are our three categories for RAIDs.
Now, if you have a failure-resistant RAID,
that's going to be something
like a RAID 1 or a RAID 5 because
it's going to protect against
the loss of the array's data
if a single disk fails inside of it.
Now, we talk about
fault-tolerant disk systems,
this will be something like
a RAID 1 or a RAID 5 again,
or even RAID 6, because even
if a single component fails
one of those drives or even
one of the cards inside of it,
then that RAID can continue
to function properly.
Now, our final category is
known as disaster-tolerant,
and so if we call a
RAID disaster-tolerant,
this means that the RAIDs
has two independent zones
with full access to the data at all times.
A RAID 10 is a good example
of a disaster-tolerant RAID,
but so is a RAID 01.
A RAID 01? What's that?
Well, if I create this RAID 01,
I'm going to have a striped array
made up of two mirrored
RAID 1, and by doing this,
I could lose either half of the array
and one of those RAID 1 are
going to still function,
and that means the system is
still going to keep functioning
and is going to make it disaster-tolerant
because I have a full copy of that data
ready to go at all times.
Now RAIDs are a great thing to use
when you're trying to
ensure you good redundancy
of your data, online and
available at all times.
This helps increase our
availability portion
of the CIA triad, and it
helps us when we're designing
a high availability system.
(soft music)