- SSL and TLS provide the
backbone of web security.
We've already talked a
lot about SSL and TSL
every time we've talked about HTTPS.
But we're going to cover
a couple more details
inside of this lesson.
First, SSL and TLS, what are they?
Well, SSL stands for
the secure socket layer.
And TLS stands for
transport layer security.
These are cryptographic protocols
that provide secure
internet communications
for web browsing, instant
messaging, email, VoIP,
and many other services.
I know we talk a lot
about it in web browsing,
but it can be used for all
of these other things too.
Now when we talk about SSL and TLS
let's start with SSL because
it's the older protocol.
SSL was what was created first.
It was a way to start securing the web
as we wanted to start doing E-commerce.
The last time SSL was updated though
was 1996 with SSL version three.
It's really old.
You shouldn't use SSL.
Instead, it's been replaced by TLS,
transport layer security.
Now, everyone watching this
should be using TLS version 1.2
which is the latest and greatest right now
as of this filming.
But, right around the corner
version 1.3 is going to be released.
The first drafts of it
are supposed to be coming out in 2019.
And then it's going to go into
widespread use in 2019 or 2020
as we keep moving forward
and increasing that security.
Now often you're going to
hear people call it SSL
even if it's TLS that you're using.
This is just something that
people call it incorrectly
because it's a creature of habit.
They've been using SSL since the 90s
and if you're an old guy like me,
you've been using it this whole time
and you call it secure socket layer
as opposed to transport layer security.
Whether you hear somebody say SSL or TLS,
most of the time they're
really referring to TLS.
Now, we've already covered
how TLS and SSL work
when we talked about the PKI lesson.
We talked about, if you remember,
that the web browser goes out
and gets the server's public key.
It then takes that and it encrypts
a random string of numbers,
sends that over to the web server.
And once the web server
gets it they decrypt it
using their private key.
They then create a symmetric
tunnel between the two.
And that symmetric tunnel,
that is SSL or TLS.
Most of the time it's TLS.
Now, again, that's because
TLS is what's current and new
and that's what you should be using.
So we've already talked
about how this works.
But, I want to talk
about how it can be used
with different protocols.
The first one is HTTPS which
we were just discussing.
Now, TLS operates below
these other protocols.
For example, if you want
to run a secure website,
you would tunnel the normal HTTP protocol
through a TLS tunnel.
Normally you'd use HTTP over port 80.
But when you tunnel it through SSL or TLS
you're going to end up
putting it on port 443
which is secure HTTP or HTTPS.
Next, let's talk about emails.
Let's say I wanted to
send an email to you.
Normally I'm going to use
SMTP and send it over port 25.
But if I want to do that securely,
I want to establish a TLS tunnel first.
I'll establish that TLS
tunnel over port 465 instead
and send my SMTP traffic
through that tunnel.
Again, it's the same
thing we did with web,
but now we're doing it with email.
And you can do that for instant messaging.
You can do it for a file transfer.
You can do it for all sorts of stuff.
Now, one of the things we
have to be concerned with
with TLS is how people can attack it.
And one of the most common
ways people attack it
is by doing a downgrade attack.
A downgrade attack is when a protocol
is tricked into using
a lower-quality version
instead of using the
higher-quality version
that is was supposed to.
So, if your server was set up
to be able to use version 1.2 of TLS,
but somebody has their browser report
that they only support 1.0,
your server may downgrade itself to 1.0
which is a weaker protocol
and can be exploited.
Now, why does it work that way?
Well, we know if somebody connects
to your website originally,
the first thing that your web
server, and that client does
is negotiate how they're going to talk.
And if I say to you, hey,
I only talk at version 1.0,
and you want to be able to support me,
you're going to downgrade to 1.0.
To stop this, you can
configure your web server
to not support downgraded versions
and say we're only going
to support version 1.1
or 1.2 for example.
This is a configuration you
can make inside your server.
And check your server documentation
whether it's Windows or Linux
on how to do this specifically
as you get into the field.
For the Security Plus exam
you need to understand
the concept of downgrade,
not how to actually secure it
by doing the hands-on
keyboard type of stuff.
The last thing I want to mention about TLS
is while it is great and
provides us lots of security,
as network defenders it's
actually a challenge for us.
Let me use this example.
You're sitting at your computer at work.
And you decide to get on Dropbox.
Well, if you're on Dropbox
and you're using the secure
version of that website,
you have a nice TLS
connection from your device
all the way to Dropbox's servers.
Well guess what?
Whenever you're putting files into there,
as a defender I can't
see what you're doing
because there's this tunnel
that I'm not a part of.
And so it's going to be
secure from your computer,
your laptop all the way to the server.
Well, if I need to see what's coming in
and out of the network, I
have to have a way to do that.
And the way I do that is what's
called break and inspect.
We talked about this back in web proxies.
If I can act as the man in the middle
by putting a proxy there,
you can connect to the proxy,
the proxy connects to Dropbox.
Now you're going to
authenticate with the proxy
with a TLS tunnel.
Then I'm going to
unencrypt what you gave me,
I'm going to look at it, inspect it,
and then I'm going to encrypt
it again and send it off
through a secure tunnel
all the way to Dropbox.
And when the files come back
I can do the same thing.
This is how I can determine
what's coming in and out
of my network and looking at it
and making sure there's no malware
or any bad things coming in or out.
Now, by doing this I'm
going to end up eating up
a lot of processor resources.
Because I have to decrypt and
encrypt every single thing
that's going through that
break and inspect proxy.
And so when you set this up
you have to make sure you set it up right.
And if you have a really
large organization,
it gets really hard to
do this effectively.