- Biometric readers.
Biometrics rely on
physical characteristics,
to identify a person properly.
This is most commonly done
by using your fingerprints,
by scanning the retina inside your eye,
or by measuring the distance,
between different parts of your face.
Now if you remember all the way back,
to section one of this course,
we talked about the five
factors of authentication.
This was something you
know, something you have,
something you are, something you do,
and somewhere you are.
Now when we talk about biometrics,
we're focused on that third
factor: something you are.
Because this is some part of you.
It's your eye, it's your
fingerprint, it's your voice,
it's something that is innately,
part of your ability
and part of your person.
Now when we talk about fingerprints,
fingerprints have become,
a very common identification system.
At this point it's even
gone beyond door locks,
and it's now integrated
into our smart phones,
and our lap tops for log in.
For example if you have an
iPhone between a 5s model,
all the way up through the eight series,
those have a thumbprint
long in called touch ID.
Whenever you press your index finger,
or your thumb to the
sensor it will log you in.
Now the newest iPhones have
done away with touch ID,
in favor of face ID.
So if you have an iPhone X or newer,
they actually have the front
facing camera scan your face,
and measure the distance between,
different areas of your face
to uniquely identify you.
This allows you to just
hold up the phone in front,
and it logs you in automatically,
by identifying that it is
you that's holding the phone.
These types of devices
are also being integrated,
into door locks and physical
access control systems,
like man traps.
I used to work in one high security area,
where every day you had
to use a retina scan,
to gain access to the facility.
I've also worked in places that have used,
a fingerprint and a pin number.
that allowed you to
get through a man trap.
It really does depend on how
your system wants to be set up,
and how your organization
views it's security practices.
Now with biometrics we do have,
a couple of challenges
that we have to focus on.
Namely the acceptance and rejection rates.
Obviously since we're using biometrics,
as a form of authentication,
we should be worried about
it's false acceptance rate.
The false acceptance rate or FAR,
is the rate that the system
authenticates a user as valid,
even though that person
should not have been,
granted access to the system.
For example if you walked up
to the fingerprint reader,
placed your finger on
it and it accepts you,
because the system though you were me,
that would be considered
a false acceptance.
To prevent unauthorized people,
from entering the building
or using our system,
we would want to ideally get
that false acceptance rate,
down to zero by increasing the
sensitivity of our scanners.
Now on the other side of the spectrum,
we have a false rejection.
And a lot of people don't think,
a false rejections a problem,
but it is just as big of a
problem as a false acceptance.
Let's go back to the last example.
If I increase the sensitivity
of the fingerprint scanner,
to attempt to eliminate all,
of the false acceptance rates or FAR,
I may inadvertently increase
my false rejection rate or FRR.
A false rejection occurs any time,
the biometrics system denies a user,
who should have been allowed
access to the system.
So using that log in
example with my finger,
let's assume that you were able to,
log in as me using your fingerprint.
So I increase that sensitivity
up to it's highest level.
Now there's no more false
acceptances occurring.
But about half of the time,
when I try to log in I'm being rejected.
Even though I'm an authorized user.
Now this is the idea of a false rejection,
and why it's also
considered a big problem.
Because if it's failing to allow me,
to authenticate half of the time,
that means half the time
I can't get to work.
So how can I perfectly tune the system,
to eliminate the false acceptance
and the false rejection?
Well I try to achieve a balance,
where the false acceptance rate,
and the false rejection rate become equal.
This is known as the
equal error rate or ERR,
more commonly though
you'll see this called,
the crossover error rate
or CER out in the industry.
This is because your
false acceptance rate,
and your false rejection rate,
intersect at that crossover
error rate or CER.
The crossover error rate uses a measure,
of the effectiveness of a
given biometrics system.
So when you're looking to purchase one,
you can use this as a factor,
in your decision making process.
You want one that doesn't have,
a huge error to the positive side,
or a huge error to the negative side.
If you can get one that has
a good crossover error rate,
that's going to make
sure that your people,
are getting authenticated
when you should be,
and rejected when they should be.
(electrical arc zaps quietly)