- In this demonstration, I'm
going to show you how to use
the Local Group Policy editor to set up
some various configurations
for your machine.
We're going to use a
Windows 10 workstation here
as our example machine,
and we're going to go
and do an application whitelist and
an application blacklist
using the Group Policy Editor.
To access the Group Policy Editor,
we simply need to go and
start up the GP Edit Program,
so we'll go ahead and
use Edit Group Policy,
and let me go ahead and make this larger.
And you'll see, down the left side,
all of the various configurations
we can do on a per user
or per computer basis.
We're going to start with
the per computer basis
with Windows settings.
Next, we're going to look
at the security settings.
And under here, we have Account Policies,
which show our Password Policies,
as well as Local Policies,
which will allow us
to do auditing user rights
and security options.
But what I want to focus on here
is application control, so we go into
our Application Control policies,
which will allow us to create
whitelists and blacklists.
If I go ahead and hit the down arrow,
you'll see we have AppLocker.
AppLocker will allow us
to create different rules
for installers, for
scripts, for packaged apps,
and what we're going to use right now,
which is Executable Rules.
Underneath the Executable
Rules, you will see
we currently have no items listed,
because this is a brand new computer.
I'm going to create a whitelist here
and allow a certain application to be run.
To do that, we simply right
click and create a new rule.
From here, we're going to be
able to walk through the Wizard
and you'll set up your permissions.
Is this going to be an Allow Rule,
meaning it's a whitelist rule,
or a Deny rule, meaning
it's a blacklist rule.
In my case, I'm going
to create a Deny Rule,
and I'm going to blacklist a program.
Next, we're going to say what conditions
are going to be met.
Is it based on the person who wrote it,
the publisher?
Like I can block all
programs that were made
by Microsoft, or by Adobe, if I wanted to.
Or, is it based on path, a
certain file and folder name?
Or, if it's a piece of malware,
you might want to do it
based on a file hash,
because every file has
its own unique hash,
as we'll talk about when we
get to hashes in cryptography.
For right now, I'm going
to use the path option
just to show you how this
works for an example.
Next, we're going to find that file.
You can browse and you
can block things based on
the folder it sits in
or a particular file.
For example, I might
want to make it so that
nobody can run any files out of the
C Drive and under the Temp folder,
which is underneath the Windows folder.
So, if I go and click down there,
I'll find the Temp folder,
and then I'll hit "Okay".
This says that anything
that's trying to be run
out of the Temporary directory
is not going to be allowed.
This is actually a good rule to set up
because a lot of malware likes to try
to run out of the Temp folder.
Then we'll go ahead and click "Next",
and you'll see that we have whatever
exceptions we want to do.
Maybe I want to say that
I will allow nothing
to run out of the Temp
folder except for Microsoft,
and so I can actually browse through
and find that reference
file for Microsoft.
In my case, I'm going to block
everything coming from that Temp folder.
And, I'm going to give it a rule.
The rule name is going to
be "block files from running
out of temp directory."
This is just used to give you a way
to remember what that rule is used for,
and you can now see that, by default,
everyone is allowed
to let anything run from
the Programs folder.
They can also allow
anything to be run from
the Windows folder, and
they can allow all files.
But, everyone is being blocked
from running out of the Temp directory.
That's the way we create
whitelist and blacklist rules.
In this example, I showed
you a blacklist rule,
but you can go through
and play around with it
and do the exact same thing
to put whitelist rules
where you would deny
everything by default,
and only allow specific programs
and files that you specify.