- So, now that I scared
you with all of the threats
that exists against virtual machines
let's talk about how we
can best secure them.
Most of the things that we need to do
to secure a virtual
machine are very similar
to things we need to
do to secure a regular
physical server too.
This includes things like
updating your operating system
in your applications.
Also, you need to ensure
that each virtual machine
has a good anti-virus solution installed.
With its own software
firewall, good strong passwords
and good policies and all of
the other security features
that we're going to discuss
throughout this course.
For this lesson, let's focus specifically
on how to secure virtual machines though.
First, remember that the
hypervisor whether it's a type one,
type two or application
containerization based model,
needs to be updated and secured
whenever the manufacturer
releases a new security patch.
For example, if an export have
been discovered then you can
now conduct a VM escape against VM ware,
you can be certain that accompanying
like VM ware is going to
quickly release a patch to fix
this critical vulnerability.
Next you want to ensure that you
limit the type of connections
that is existing between
the virtual machine
and the physical machine.
This can be represented by
a virtualized network card,
or even as network shares.
As I'm going to demonstrate
in the next lesson.
Remember if a virtual machine
gets infected with malware
it should remain isolated from
all the other virtual machine
hosted by the same hypervisor.
But only if you implement
your configurations
for isolation correctly.
Just like a physical server
anytime there is a connection
between a virtual machine
and a shared resource,
something like a network file server.
This is an opportunity for
data to be passed between
the different virtual machines,
and this would break down the isolation
that you may be achieving.
Just like we discussed back
in handling our operating
systems we want to minimize
and remove any features that
are not needed to support our operations.
When dealing with the virtual machine,
remember that hardware is
emilated and it can be removed
just like a piece of softare
would be under normal machine.
If don't your virtual machine
to have an emilated flappy
disk or CD drive for example,
you can simply remove those features.
This in turn will
minimize your text surface
and remove potential vulnerabilities.
All of your virtual machines
are hosted on physical
computers or servers.
And so if you had many
virtual machine residing
on a same physical server,
and an attack is able to compromise
one of those virtual machines,
they maybe able to force
it to use a large amount of
physical server resources.
If they do this can affect the
other virtual machines hosted
on that same server.
In fact this could result and
denial servers for one or more
of the virtual machines being hosted.
To minimize this threat you
should consider spreading out
your virtual machines among
several physical servers.
In steady of relying on one
single physical server to host
every single virtual machine.
As assessment administrator,
its also important to keep
tracking your virtual machines
and where they are being deployed.
Each virtual machine represents
a fully operating system
and therefore you have to
ensure you're doing proper
patch management,
to make sure all of these
virtual machines stay up to date.
Additionally it becomes common
for Virtualization Sprawl
to occur within an organization.
Virtualization Sprawl refers
to when virtual machines are
created, used and deployed
without proper oversight
governance or management by
the system administrators.
Because virtual machines only exists
as a file on some server,
it's really easy to loose track of them.
And you'll not remember
where you've actually
deployed them all.
And when it comes time to
update them or retire them
you sometimes just lose track.
Finally it's important to enable
encryption of the file that
host the virtual machines as well.
In the next lesson I'm going
to demonstrate how easy it is
to encrypt your virtual
machine files to keep them safe
from prying eyes on the server.
This will make sure that
when you're deploying them
and using them in your network,
everything remain safe and confidential.