- In this demonstration,
you're going to learn how
to create a software RAID
on a Windows machine.
My machine has a few hard drives,
and we're going to go ahead and use
the Windows disk management tool
to setup two different RAID systems on it.
Now, one is going to be a RAID 0,
which is going to provide us
with more speed and performance
by splitting the data
being read and write,
into to two separate drives
on two different disks.
Now, each disk is going
to get half of the data.
This means, if I lose one of the drives,
I'm going to lose all of the data.
Now, on the other hand, I'm
going to create a second RAID.
This is going to be a RAID 1,
which allows us to have two hard disks
operating in a mirror.
So, both disks are going to have
exactly the same data on 'em.
This means I'm not going to
get the performance boost
I get with a RAID 0,
but I do get redundancy.
So, if one disk fails,
the other disk is still
going to be maintaining
a fully online and ready to use copy
of all of the data and information.
Now, let's go ahead and jump into the lab,
and let me show you how to
create these two types of RAIDs.
So, on this Windows 10 machine,
I current have a C drive
with the operating system installed,
and I have four blank disks
that have been installed.
I'm going to go ahead and
go to my disk management,
and inside my disk management,
under computer management,
you will see that I have four
disks that are brand new.
I'm going to go ahead
and initialize those.
Now that I've initialized them,
I have these four unallocated disks
sitting here at the bottom,
and my current C drive.
So, what I want to do is,
I want to create two different RAIDs.
I'm going to create one for video editing,
which means I want
performance over redundancy.
So, what I'm going to do is,
I'm going to right click on my first disk,
and go to new striped volume.
Because, I'm going to stripe
across disk one and disk two
to make my RAID 0, to give
me that performance I want.
As I walk through the wizard,
I'm going to add the second disk to it.
So, I have disk one and disk two,
then I'm going to go down next,
I'm going to give it a drive letter.
In this case, I'm just going to
go ahead and call it drive D.
Hit next.
I'm going to give it a name.
I'm going to call it editing,
because I'm going to use
it for video editing.
And then, I'll hit next.
And then, we'll finish.
And, we'll say yes,
and off it goes.
I now have, drive D,
which is 1.57 terabytes,
and I have 100% free,
because I have two, 800 gigabyte drives
working in tandem to give me
that one, logical drive, drive D.
But, if either of those disks fails,
drive D will be gone.
Now, let's go ahead and
create a redundant drive,
which is going to be drive three and four.
I'm going to add them
together as a mirrored volume.
Now, when I add both of those in,
I'm going to get two disks,
but I'm only going to get
one disk's worth of space.
I'm going to call this R for redundancy.
And so, over here for R, I'm
going to call it redundant,
and we'll go ahead and format it.
And notice, I now have
this redundant drive,
which is called drive R.
And, drive R is a mirrored drive,
it is going to be dynamic.
And you'll notice that it
only has a capacity size
of one of those drives,
because one is acting as primary
and one is acting as
backup, where both of them
have the exact same information.
And, if either of them goes offline,
the other drive will still take over.
That gives me my fault tolerance,
and that creates a 50% overhead,
or a loss of one drive's worth of space.
But, that's the sacrifice.
Do you want performance,
and double the space?
Or, do you want redundancy,
and half the space?
That's the choice that we're making here.
Now, in my case I chose both.
I wanted one drive as my scratch drive
for all my video editing,
and I wanted my redundant drive to be
where I store the finished products,
and it gives me that redundancy
that I was looking for.
(electronic music)