- Authentication.
As the security of our networks
becomes more important
to our organizations,
we have to continue to seek better ways
to increase that security.
Now although many organizations have been
increasingly adding
difficult password schemes
to create a more secure network
such as using things like upper case
and lower case letters,
numbers,
symbols
and passwords over 14
characters in length,
studies have shown
that the use of
multi-factor authentication,
is exponentially more secure.
Now what exactly is
multi-factor authentication?
Well, it's the use of two or more means
to prove a user's identity.
There are five basic
factors of authentication
that you can consider when determining
if is who they say they are.
They are knowledge,
ownership,
characteristic,
location
and action.
Now the knowledge factor is concerned
with the user providing a
piece of memorized information.
This can be a password,
a pin,
a combination to a lock,
their mother's maiden name,
their social security number,
their birthday,
their place of birth
or any other piece of information
that can be memorized
and recited when they're asked for it.
The second factor is what we
call the ownership factor.
Now an ownership factor
is concerned with a user
proving that they have
something in their possession
that uniquely identifies them.
In the real world,
this might be something like
pulling out your driver's
license or your passport.
Now in the electronic world though,
we use other things.
Things like token devices
that are small handheld device
that has a randomly generated code
that changes every 30 to 60 seconds
that the server and the client both know.
It could be something like a smart card
that you insert into a card reader
on your desktop that gives you access.
It could be a USB dongle
where you plug it in
and that gives you access.
Or it can be an authentication mechanism
that sends you a unique and random number
each time you try to log in
and they text that to you
and you then enter back in
showing that you have physical possession
of your cellphone
that accesses your token.
The third thing we have is what's called
the characteristic factor.
Now a characteristic is defined
as something that the person is.
This is usually accomplished
using some form of bio-metric technology.
Like a fingerprint scanner,
an iris reader
or a facial recognition unlock feature.
For example,
on the old iPhone 5S,
they had a fingerprint reader
embedded into the home button
and you put your thumb on there
and that would unlock the phone.
Now on the newer iPhones,
the iPhone X's,
they utilize a dual front facing camera
that's going to scan your face
and figure out if it is you
based on the distance
between different features,
like your nose to your ear.
Another form of this,
is called a vocal pattern recognition
where someone is going to speak
and it's going to pick out
the pattern of your voice,
to uniquely identify you.
This is something that
banks are beginning using
to uniquely identify their
customers over the phone
before helping them with
the customer service.
Now the fourth factor we have,
is called location.
This factor refers to where a person is
when they're trying to
log into their account.
For example,
I tend to travel a lot for work.
When I attempt to log
into my Gmail account
when I'm traveling,
their system can sometimes
flag that as unusual,
and they'll ask me for a second piece
of information to verify,
I am who I say I am.
You're organization may require a user
to be within a certain city,
a state or country before they can log in
based on the GPS of your
device or the IP address
from where you're attempting access.
Our fifth and final factor,
is called action.
An action refers to
something that a user does.
This isn't a commonly used
factor in many networks though.
The action factor can be something
that talks about how
you perform something.
For example,
the way you draw a picture,
or the way you sign your name,
could be used as an action factor.
So now that we covered the five factors,
I want to drive home a really
important concept for the exam.
If you're only using one of these factors
at a time to identify your user,
this is called single-factor
authentication.
Now sometimes you can have two
or more things being asked for,
but they're all the same
type of one of these five.
For example,
if I say you logged in
using your username and your password,
this is two things.
Is this multi-factor or
single-factor authentication?
Well, because a username and a password
are both something you know,
or a knowledge factor,
this is still considered
single-factor authentication.
This is an important concept
to understand for the exam.
Now to increase security,
we want to use at least two
factors of authentication
creating dual-factor or
multi-factor authentication.
For example,
if you had a smart card
token and a pin number,
that's something you have,
possession,
and something you know,
knowledge.
You put these together,
that gives you two factors
which is multi-factor authentication.
Now this is going to be a lot more secure,
because you have two different things
that the person has to have
to be able to get into your system.
Security is constantly evolving,
and so we're always adding additional
mechanisms of authentication.
The most securities is what we call,
the one-time used password.
These are implemented
generally using either
a time-based or a hash-based mechanism.
Now with a Time-based
One Time used Password,
or a TOTP,
a password is computed from
a shared secret and a current time.
This is often used with RSA key fobs,
where they create a
seemingly random number
that's displayed on this ownership factor,
and then you're going to type that in
and the server and the
client both would know it,
but nobody else will.
And since these passwords are constantly
changing every 30 or 60 seconds,
they can only be used one time,
before they start changing again.
Now this time-based approach
is actually a variation
of the hash-based approach
known as the HMAC-based One Time
Password algorithm or HOTP.
This algorithm actually
computes a password
from a shared secret
and it's synchronized
across both the client and the server.
Each time that password
is entered in to log in,
a new password is created
using this hash-based algorithm
and it's synchronized between the client
and the server making sure
that it's only used one time.
As you can see,
there are a lot of ways
to conduct authentication.
In this section of the course,
we're going to focus
exclusively on authentication,
the different technologies
and the different
mechanisms that are used.