- Switches can also provide the ability
to create virtual local area networks.
This adds a layer of
separation to our networks
without requiring us to
buy additional switches
that have to be configured
and installed on the network.
VLANs are implemented
to segment our network,
reduce collisions, organize our networks,
boost performance and increase security.
Unfortunately attackers
have created VLAN hopping
which allows them to
break out of our VLANs
and access other VLAN data though.
There's a couple of mechanisms to do this.
The first method is
known as switch spoofing.
In this attack, an attacker
essentially configures
their device to pretend that it's a switch
and they connect to a switch port
to negotiate a trunk link
and break out of the VLAN.
To prevent this, you can disable
dynamic trunking protocol
or DTP on all your switch ports,
place all your unplugged
ports into an unused VLAN,
explicitly forward frames
and avoid default VLAN names.
The second method is what's
known as double tagging.
As traffic goes across a switch,
it reads the outermost VLAN tag first,
strips it off and then routes the traffic
to the proper VLAN.
In double tagging though,
an attacker actually adds two VLAN tags,
an outer tag and an inner tag,
so as traffic goes
through the first switch,
it removes the outer tag
and is then forwarded to the
destination of the inner tag.
You can prevent this by
moving all the ports out
of the default VLAN group.
Double tagging can also be prevented
by upgrading your switch's firmware,
utilizing an unused
VLAN as the default VLAN
and redesigning the VLAN structures.