- In security one of the
most important things
is to ensure that you understand,
what openings you have
created in your systems.
When it comes to computers and networks,
most of these openings are
going to be created by ports.
Now a port is simply a
logical communication endpoint
that exists on your
computer or your server.
For example, if you're
running a web server,
you're going to have port 80 open
and listening for inbound requests
from your potential visitors.
Now ports are classified as either
inbound or outbound ports.
An inbound port is used
when your computer or server
is listening for a connection.
Just as in my earlier example,
the web server had port 80
open, that's an inbound port.
It's just waiting for
somebody to come along
and connect to it.
An outbound port on the other
hand, is opened by a computer
whenever it wants to connect to a server.
If my computer is attempting
to make a connection
to your web server over port 80,
well, then my computer is going to open up
a random high number
port such as port 52363
and it's going to make an outbound
request to that web server.
Now, what does all this
look like in the real world?
Well, let's look at an
example of how an inbound
and outbound port are used when my laptop
attempts to connect to a
remote server over SSH.
First, we have a server
at the top of the screen
and it has a public IP
address assigned to it,
and it's listening on port 22,
so port 22 is the inbound
port awaiting new connections.
And in this case, port 22 is open.
At the bottom of the screen,
I have my laptop that wants
to make the connection.
Now, my laptop has a
private IP address assigned
because my network is
using NAT at the router
and that gives me some
additional protections.
So, notice at this point
my laptop doesn't have
any ports opened yet.
So now my laptop wants to go
and establish the SSH connection.
It's going to open up an
outbound port on itself,
which is going to be some random
high number port like 51233
and it's going to send a
request to the SSH server
over port 22 which is
the server's inbound port
and destined for it's IP address
in this case, 46.124.63.13.
Now once a server receives this request,
it has to respond to it.
So, it's going to send a
packet of information back
to my laptop's IP in the
outbound port that was open.
In this case that's port
51233 and in reality
it would be the public facing
IP address of my router
but for our example, I'm going
to use the private IP address
of 192.168.1.45.
Now, that my laptop has made
the request to the server
and the server answered that request,
we now have a session established
and both devices can communicate
back and forth as needed.
Once that session is over,
the connection is going to be closed,
my laptop is going to
close it's outbound port
because it's no longer needed
and the server will keep
that inbound port open
so they can receive
requests from the next user
who wants to use it.
So now that we showed how
ports work in the real world,
let's talk a little bit more
about the ports themselves.
In addition to being called
inbound and outbound ports,
the ports are going to
be assigned a number.
Now, the number can be
anywhere between 0 and 65,535
but this big range is
actually divided into
three smaller groups.
The first group is called
the Well-Known ports.
This is for any ports that
are between 0 and 1023.
These are called Well-Known ports
because they are designated by IANA
the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority
and they are going to
assign it to commonly used
protocols and ports.
Now, for example secure web
browsing is one we all know.
It's https and it uses port 443,
Telnet is another well-known
one, it's port 23.
Both of these are
considered well-known ports
as well as hundreds of others.
Now, the second group we
have is going to cover ports
from 1024 up to 49,151.
This range is called the registered ports
because they have to be used by vendors
for their own proprietary protocols
and each vendor is going to register them
with IANA prior to using them.
For example Microsoft has an SQL server
and it uses port 1433 which
is another registered port.
Another good example of this
is remote desktop protocol
which is a proprietary Microsoft protocol
called RDP. It operates on port 3389.
The third and final group
is called the dynamic and private ports.
This uses the ports between
49,151 all the way up to 65,535.
These ports can be used by any application
at any time without having to
be registered with IANA first.
Now, this range is usually
used by your client
whenever it picks a
random high number port
for its application.
Anytime it wants to have a
temporary outbound connection
this is the range that it's going to use.
This is also commonly used in gaming
as well as instant message and chat.
(soft music)