- We all use wireless devices these days.
Whether it's your laptop, your
tablet, or your smartphone,
all of these have the ability
to communicate wirelessly.
How can we best secure these devices?
Well, there's two main things
we have to think about when
we talk about wireless with these devices:
wifi and Bluetooth.
First, wifi, is there
internet connectivity?
If we're using wifi, we want
to make sure the wifi is set
to be protected at the highest levels.
Currently, that's WPA2, or Wifi Protected
Access Version Two.
This relies on the advanced
encryption standard
for its encryption
algorithm, also known as AES.
In addition to securing our
wifi, we also have to consider
the peripherals that
connect to these devices.
For example, if you have a
smartphone and it connects
to a Bluetooth to your car,
how is that link being secured?
Well, by default, Bluetooth
requires you to pair the device
and when you pair the
device, the two devices will
communicate via that shared
link in giving each other
a shared link key.
They use that key to encrypt their data.
Unfortunately, some of these
devices use weaker encryption
than others, so if you're
really worried about
your confidentiality, you
should always try to avoid
wireless devices when possible.
If you have to use a wireless
device like headphones
or connecting to your car, you should look
at the manufacturer specifications
to determine what type
of encryption is being used
and if they're not using AES
with a strong key, you might
want to pass on using that
device and buy a replacement.
(light music)