- Hijacking, next we have hijacking
which is the exploitation
of a computer session
in an attempt to gain
unauthorized access to data,
services, or other resources
on a computer or server.
There are eight types of session hijacking
that can be performed.
Session theft, TCP/IP
hijacking, blind hijacking,
clickjacking, Man-in-the-Middle,
Man-in-the-Browser, the
watering hole attack
and cross-site-scripting attacks.
The first type of hijacking
is known as session theft.
With session theft the
attacker is going to guess
the session ID for a web session
and that enables them to takeover
the already authorized
and established session
of that client.
Each session is uniquely
identified with a random string
but if the attacker can
determine or guess that string
they can take over the
authenticated session
with the server.
And this example, you
can see this is occurring
at the session layer of the OSI model
but it can also occur at the
network or transport layer too.
Now when it does it's
called TCP/IP hijacking.
Because it occurs when an
attacker takes over a TCP session
between two computers
without the need of a cookie
or other host access.
Because TCP sessions only authenticate
during the initial three-way handshake
the attacker can jump into the session
at any time they want if they can guess
the next number in the packet sequence.
This can also be used to create
a denial of service attack
against the initial host that
way they can take it over
and not let that person
jump back into the session.
Now, the next type of hijacking
is called blind hijacking
because it occurs when the attacker
blindly injects data into
a communication stream
and won't be able to see the results
whether they're successful or not.
Clickjacking is our next type.
This attack uses multiple
transparent layers
to trick a user into clicking
on a button or link on a page
when they were intending
to click on something else.
Basically the hyperlink
to the malicious content
is hidden under some
legitimate clickable content.
So you think you're clicking on an image
and you're actually clicking on some link
that takes you elsewhere.
Now a Man-in-the-Middle attack
is probably the attack
you've heard most before.
This is also one that is commonly
used in session hijacking.
A Man-in-the-Middle attack causes data
to flow through the attacker's computer
where it can then be intercepted
or manipulated as it passes through.
This is considered an
active type of interception.
So let's pretend that you've
got some kind of malware
on your computer and
now all of your traffic
is going to route through
this attacker's machine.
Well, if you wanted to transfer $50
from your bank account to your friend's
but the attacker changes the amount
and the destination of the account
you may now be sending
$5000 to the attacker
instead of the $50 to your friend.
This is the idea of a Man-in-the-Middle.
Since the attacker is sitting
right in the middle of that connection
they can see and manipulate any data
as it's being sent back and forth.
Now a Man-in-the-Browser is very similar
to the Man-in-the-Middle
except it's limited to your
browser's web communication
instead of looking at
the entire communication.
This can occur because you have a Trojan
that's infected your
vulnerable web browser
and it modifies web pages or transactions
that are being done within that browser.
To prevent this you should insure
you have a good anti-malware
solution installed
and you have the latest security updates
for your web browser
because this will pretty much eliminate
the Man-in-the-Browser attack.
Next you have a watering hole.
And a watering hole is
something that we described
all the way back in the
beginning of this course.
It occurs when malware
is laced on a website
that the attacker knows
his potential victims
are going to access.
Now this can also be modified
to allow for session hijacking too
because the attacker can
takeover that website
and grab the information
between your client and the server itself.
Finally we have cross-site-scripting
which we've also discussed before.
Now I'm mentioning it here briefly
because cross-site-scripting
is another way
that you can use this vulnerability
to conduct session
hijacking against a victim.
It does this by targeting
that client's computer
and tricking it into
thinking the code came
from a trusted web server.
And if you can trick it successfully
then the client is going
to execute that code
and this can give that
attacker a hijack place
inside that communication stream.