- [Instructor] In this
demonstration I'm going to show you
how a Buffer Overflow Attack is conducted.
Now, I'm going to do this by using
a simple program that's written here.
This program is called Narnia 0.C.
This tells me that the program was written
in the C programming language.
You can see it displayed
here on the screen.
Now you don't have to be
an expert in the C language
to understand what this
program is doing, though.
I'm going to walk you
through it step by step.
And then I'm going to
show you how we throw this
Buffer Overflow Attack
too exploit this program.
Now the first thing that we
can see is that there are
two statements that start
with the word include.
This is just saying that
were going to include
these third-party libraries.
The standard input output library,
and the standard library itself.
After those two include statements
we get the main part of this program.
This is called Main.
If you see the first thing,
we have a long variable.
And that value is 0x
four one, four one, four one, four one.
Followed by that, we
have a character array
being set up called Buffer,
that is 20 items long.
This means that the buffer can only hold
20 pieces of information, or
20 characters, in this case.
Next we have the print F statement.
Which basically says
put everything in between
the quotes onto the screen
when you run this program.
Then, if it goes and asks you
here is your chance to try it.
And then it asks by scanning
what the input is from the keyboard.
And that input is going to
be stored into the buffer.
Once you've inputted what
you want to the buffer,
it's going to print out the two variables.
What's stored in buffer,
and what's stored in value.
After displaying both
variables to the screen
it's going to see what the value was.
If the value equals 0x DEADBEEF,
meaning we've overflowed the buffer
with the characters that make up DEADBEEF
then the system will
give you a shell prompt.
Which means you're going to
have access to that system
to conduct any kind of programs you want.
If not, it's going to say way off
and it's going to exit the program.
And you'll have to try again.
So now that we've walked
through that program a bit
let's go ahead and run
it and see how it works.
First we'll type in ./narnia0
which simply tells a computer
to run the program Narnia0.
When I hit enter you'll
see that it brings up
the correct value is from
41, 41, 41, 41 to DEADBEEF.
Here is your chance, and it's
asking you to input something.
So now I need to input my guess.
What I'm going to do, is
I'm going to put in 20 A's
and four B's.
The buffer, if you remember,
was only 20 characters long.
So what I'm really trying to do here
is fill up that 20 character buffer
using all of the A's,
and those four B's are going to overflow
into the value of the variable val.
So instead of having four one,
four one, four one, four one
I'm going to have the
hex value of those 4 B's.
And when I do that you'll see
that the buffer is now flowing
with all of those A's, and those four B's
and the value has changed
from four one, four
one, four one, four one,
to four two, four two, four two, four two.
And four two, is the hex
representation of the letter B.
So now at this point
I'm going to go through
and try to write a short python script
that will put 20 A's followed by some
hexadecimal characters that I want.
In this case I want the hexadecimal value
to show up as DEADBEEF.
D-E-A-D-B-E-E-F.
Now, those are characters that
make up a word in this case
but actually they're
just hexadecimal digits.
Where the D stands for
13, the E stands for 14,
the A stands for 10, et cetera.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to have to do
this a little bit backwards,
and the reason is because
this machine is going to use
last in, first out architecture
when I'm trying to attack it.
So in this case I'm going to use /ef, /be,
/ad, /de
which when combined back together
will give me DEADBEEF like I want.
And I'm going to pipe that output
into the Narnia 0.C program.
So when I hit enter, it's
going to run that program
and feed that information from
the python script into it.
In this case, the buffer
is now overwritten
with those 20 A's,
and the four hexadecimal
characters that I've added.
And you can see that the variable val
has now been overwritten
with the value of 0x DEADBEEF.
This was the solution we
wanted in the problem.
But, all it did was return
us back to the Narnia prompt.
That's because what the
program did was run itself
and execute a shell.
But I was already in
the shell environment.
If I was doing a Buffer
Overflow Attack like this,
I can have it run any program I want.
And so to do that and
display that for you,
I'm going to go through,
and actually change
my python script just a bit here.
So I'm going to run my
python script again,
but I'm going to add a little bit to it.
So I'm going to bring it
up like I had last time
and I'm going to add a
semicolon, which means
once you've finished do that command
do this next command.
And so what I'm going to do here is echo,
and then the program cat,
and I want you to show me the file
Narnia one, inside the
Naria paths directory.
Ideally this would be
something like a password file.
Like an etc shadow file,
or something like that.
And then I'm going to
go ahead and run that.
Now let's see what happens.
In this case we see
that the DEADBEEF value
is written to the value.
But then when it goes to
execute that shell command
it was passed the command that I gave it.
The cat/etc/narnia_pass/narnia1.
And so what I get the
value shown in that file.
In this case that e-f-e-i-d-i-e-d-a-e.
Now this is just a very simplistic example
of a Buffer Overflow Attack.
If you didn't understand all of the things
that I went through in
this video, that's okay.
This is way beyond the
scope of Security Plus.
But I wanted to show you
what a Buffer Overflow Attack
really looks like when a hacker
is doing this type of thing.
This is a sample for our lab environment,
but I just wanted to give
you an idea of what happens.
And the big take away here is that
we overflowed the memory buffer,
so that whatever was put in after
went and overwrote the
next value in memory.
In our case, then val variable.
By doing that we are then
able to run other programs,
by getting into a command
shell or other things.
Whatever command that's going to be run
is going to depend on
the exploit you're using.
But that initial buffer overflow is what
allows you to put that into memory.
(frenzied electronic music)