- Fire suppression.
Now fire suppression is
the process of controlling
and/or extinguishing fires to protect
your organization's
employees, data, equipment,
and buildings.
You have to choose the right
type of fire suppression
and this is probably going
to be one of the most
important facility decisions
that your organization
is going to make to ensure
that it's long-term safety
of its employees and its
networks remains unchallenged.
Now there are three
types of fire suppression
that we have to discuss
for the Security Plus exam.
There's handheld fire extinguishers,
sprinkler systems, and special
hazard protection systems
that we use especially
in our server rooms.
Now let's discuss handheld
extinguishers first
because they're not created equally.
Each one is a little bit different.
In fact, before you choose
the proper extinguisher
you need to identify what class of fire
you're trying to put out.
Fires are broken down into
five different categories.
Class A, B, C, D, and K.
Class A fires consist of
solid combustible materials,
things like wood and paper.
To put out a Class A fire, you should use
a water-based extinguisher.
This extinguisher should have
green triangle label on it
so you can quickly identify it as
a water-based extinguisher.
I like to think of the green
triangle as a green tree
since these Class A fires
are made up of tree products.
Things like wood and paper in most cases.
Now you shouldn't use a
water-based extinguisher
in a server room because this could cause
a lot of damage to the
different components there
as well as put you in
danger of an electric shock
when that water hits something that's
electrically charged.
The second type of fire is
known as a Class B fire.
Class B fires consist of
flammable gases or liquids.
To put out a Class B fire, you should use
a dry chemical agent or a
CO2-based fire extinguisher.
These are usually
labeled with a red square
to signify that they can
be used on Class B fires.
Class C fires, on the other
hand, are electrical fires.
If you encounter an electrical fire,
the first thing you should try to do
is shut off the power to the room
because if you remove the power,
this could put out the fire for you.
If it doesn't, then you
need to extinguish that fire
with a fire extinguisher.
If you're going to use
a portable extinguisher
you should look for a
CO2-based extinguisher
or one with a blue circle
on it for Class C fires.
Next we have Class D fires
and these are made up
of combustible metals like
magnesium, titanium, and lithium.
Now, you might be wondering,
where am I going to find
these combustible metals
inside my office?
Well, most laptops have lithium batteries
so if you have a laptop
fire, you have to treat it
as a Class D fire.
To extinguish it, you should
look for an extinguisher
with a yellow decagon on
it and this extinguisher
is going to be fully yellow in color
so you can quickly and easily identify it.
Class K fires are composed of cooking oil.
So if your organization has a kitchen
inside of its facilities,
you should have a fire extinguisher system
that's built-in to handle
grease and oil fires
that could occur during cooking.
This type of fire is
symbolized by a black hexagon
and the systems that are
going to extinguish them
have that black hexagon on them as well.
Now as you walk around your
office or your facilities,
you're likely going to
see one of three types
of portable extinguishers.
The first is an ABC extinguisher,
which uses dry chemicals to put out fires.
If possible, you should avoid using this
on computer equipment though because
the dry chemical is
corrosive and destructive
to computer and electrical components.
The second and probably most common type
you're going to see is
called a BC extinguisher,
which is used on B and C fires.
This most often uses
CO2 to put out a fire.
This is useful for both
gas fires, Class B,
and electrical fires,
Class C, and it's also safe
to use on computers.
Be careful when using a
CO2 extinguisher though
because it will smother the fire by
displacing oxygen from it, which is great.
But if there's people close by
it's going to take out that
oxygen that they need to breathe
and people could have trouble breathing
if there's no oxygen in the room.
The third type is a yellow extinguisher
and these bottles are used
for Class D or metal fires.
These are less common
but you should be aware
of where they are in case you need one
inside your organization.
Now in addition to the
handheld extinguishers
your facility might use a sprinkler system
to put out fires inside the office.
Sprinkler systems can either
be wet pipe or dry pipe.
A wet pipe sprinkler
system means that there's
water already filling all
of the sprinkler pipes
and it's just waiting for
that little red glass bulb
to be broken or melt from a fire.
If that bulb melts or it's broken,
it's going to release the
water from the sprinkler system
into the office spaces to smother any fire
and release that heat.
Now in some facilities the
spaces can get really cold
and below freezing, especially
if you live in the north.
If you're in a warehouse
environment or some other
non-air-conditioned space,
you don't want water
sitting in these pipes
because they could freeze and crack.
If your facility has this issue
then you want to use a dry
pipe sprinkler system instead.
In this type of system,
the pipes are filled
with pressurized air and only
pushes water into those pipes
when it's needed to combat a fire.
This happens once that
little red bulb is broken,
once again.
The third type of sprinkler
system is known as
a pre-action sprinkler system and
it's similar to a dry pipe system,
except it also can be set off
if heat or smoke is detected
and it won't wait until
there's a full fire
that causes that red
bulb to break or melt.
Now a pre-action sprinkler
system won't activate
if the pipe or the bulb
is broken by itself
because it still has
to detect heat or smoke
before it releases its
contents into the room.
Now in most server rooms we don't want
to use a sprinkler system.
It's not a very good choice for us
and the reason is if somebody
sets off the sprinkler system
by accident, it would release
water into the server room
and it would destroy all of the servers
and other electrical components we have
by surrounding them with water.
Now for this reason, we're going to use
a special hazard protection system
instead of a sprinkler system.
This type of system is known as
a clean agent system and it will
push gas into the room instead
and that will allow it
to smother the fire.
This may be something like HALON,
which we don't use commonly anymore
here in the United States because
its bad for the environment.
Or something like FM-200
or even a CO2-based system.
If you're ever working in a server room
and you hear an alarm going off loudly,
you should immediately
drop what you're doing
and leave the room because this loud alarm
is a warning that the gas
is about to be released
into the server room and
if you remain in that room
it's going to suffocate the fire
and it's going to suffocate you.
So you need to get out immediately
when you hear that noise.
(electric guitar)