- Switches.
Now hubs were originally
used to connect devices
on a network.
All of the devices will
be connected to a hub,
and anytime something went
into one port of the hub,
it would then repeat that
out all of the other ports.
This was known as a broadcast message.
Now this is because hubs were dumb.
They had no intelligence.
As networks got larger,
hubs caused a lot of collisions
and slowed down the network.
To solve this problem,
something came along called a bridge,
and this was used to separate
physical LANs or WANs
into two logical networks,
or connect two logical networks together.
Now switches are the
evolution of hubs and bridges.
Essentially every single port on a switch
acts as if it was a
bridged hub on each one.
This means that it
improves the data transfer
and security through the intelligent use
of MAC addresses.
Being able to figure out where a device is
and only sending the information out
that particular port of the
switch and ignoring the rest.
This reduces traffic
and increases security.
Now switches are subject to three main
types of attack though.
They are subject to MAC
flooding, MAC spoofing,
and physical tampering.
This is because they're trying to overcome
that logic and intelligence
that the switch has.
MAC flooding is an attempt to overwhelm
the limited switch memory that's set aside
to store the MAC addresses for each port,
and this is known as the
content addressable memory,
or CAM table.
Now if a switch is
flooded, it can fail-open
and begin to start acting like a hub
and broadcasting data
out every single port.
This is a problem that can start causing
confidentiality to be breached
inside your local network.
Now MAC spoofing, on the other hand,
occurs when an attacker
masks their own MAC address
to pretend that they are
having the MAC address
of some other machine on the network.
For example, wireless access
points may use MAC filtering
to prevent devices that are unknown
from joining the wireless network.
They do this my looking
at their MAC address
that's being reported,
and if it's not inside
their access control list,
they'll block it from connecting.
Now if I switch my MAC address
to a known or allowed device,
I can gain access to that
network though by spoofing.
I pretend that I am an authorized device
using a known good MAC address,
and I pass right through that ACL.
MAC spoofing is also sometimes
combined with ARP spoofing.
ARP is an address resolution protocol,
and it relies on the MAC addresses
as a way of combining what
MAC address goes to which IP,
and which IP goes to which MAC address.
So they often combine a MAC
address spoof with an ARP spoof
as an attempt to be able
to have the attacker appear
that they are the
destination that somebody
is trying to send information to,
and use that as a way to
steal that information.
Now to prevent this,
you have to configure your switch
to accept limited numbers
of static MAC addresses,
limit the duration of
time that an ARP entry
is allowed on a host,
and conduct ARP inspections.
To keep track of what ARP is being used
with which MAC address and which IPs.
The third type of way
to overwhelm a switch
is to use physical tampering.
Physical tampering occurs when an attacker
attempts to gain physical
access to the switch,
because if you can touch a device,
you can pretty much configure
it to do whatever you want.
Each switch has a dedicated
management port on it,
and if an attacker can gain
access to the switch physically
by walking up to it,
they can connect their
laptop to the management port
and reconfigure that switch and
cause all sorts of problems.
Additionally, an attacker
could unplug cables,
or unplug the power itself from the switch
and this could cause a
denial of service attack.
Now to prevent physical tampering,
the switch should be locked up
in a network rack, or a network closet,
or behind closed doors so
that, that room is secure
using good physical security practices.