- This is probably one of
the most important videos
we're going to cover in the course.
Did I get your attention yet?
Here's the video that
I want you to bookmark,
take notes and even create flashcards
based on what you see.
This is so important that I just spent
the first 30 seconds
of this video stressing
how important it is.
What is it?
It's memorizing port numbers
and its associated protocols.
As I just said in the last lesson,
there are 65,536 ports
available for your computer
and your network to use.
Yes, 65,536.
And because ports can go
anywhere from port zero
all the way up to 65,535,
because computers start counting at zero,
that's how we get that number.
Now, luckily for you,
you don't have to memorize
all these 65 thousand plus ports.
But there are 35 ports that you simply
have to memorize for the exam.
To cover them I'm going to provide you
with the port number,
the protocol it's used for
and whether it relies on TCP or UDP
for its transport layer protocol.
All right, with that said,
let's get started with
the memorization of ports.
The first one is FTP or
the File Transfer Protocol.
It's used to transfer
files from host to host
and operates over port 21 using TCP.
Next we have SSH or Secure Shell.
It's used to remotely
administer network devices
and systems over port 22
using either TCP or UDP.
Also over port 22 we have
secure copy called SCP
and it's used to securely
copy files over a network.
Also on port 22 we have
SFTP or secure FTP.
It's also going to be
operated over port 22
and is a secure method of uploading
and downloading your files over a network.
Next we have Telnet which is used
to remotely administer network devices,
but it doesn't provide any security.
In fact, Telnet will send everything
over the network in an unencrypted,
clear text format making it very dangerous
for you to use.
For this reason you should disable Telnet
in your network.
For the exam remember
that Telnet is operated
over port 23 and uses both TCP and UDP.
The next one we have is
Simple Mail Transfer Protocol or SMTP.
And it's used to send
email over the Internet.
It operates over port 25
using a TCP connection.
Domain Name Service or DNS is our next one
and it's used to resolve host names to IPs
and IPs to host names.
When you look at something
like diontraining.com
and convert it to 184.168.131.241,
this is DNS operating at work.
DNS is going to operate over port 53
and uses both TCP and UDP connections.
Our next one is TFTP or Trivial FTP
and it's used as a simplified version
of FTP to put a file on a remote host
or get a file from a remote host.
It operates over port 69
using a UDP connection.
It isn't one of the most secure types
of file transfer but it is lightweight,
so often it's used to boot
a network operating system off of a server
and onto a thin-client.
HTTP or Hyper Text Transfer Protocol
is widely used.
It's used to transmit
webpage data for a client
over an unencrypted connection
whenever you're browsing the Internet.
HTTP uses port 80 and transmits using TCP.
Our next one is Kerberos.
Kerberos is used for
network authentication
using a system of tickets
within a Windows domain.
It operates using both TCP and UDP
and operates on port 88.
Next we have POP3 or the
Post Office Protocol v3
and it's used to receive
mail from a mail server.
It operates over TCP port 110.
This port is for the
unencrypted POP3 services.
We'll talk about the
encrypted version later on.
Our next one is NNTP
which is the Network
News Transfer Protocol.
It's used to transport
Usenet articles to a client.
It operates using TCP over port 119.
Next we have RPC,
the Remote Procedure Call and it's used
to locate DCOM ports to request a service
from a program on another computer
over the network.
This is commonly used in
Windows based networks
and operates using both
TCP and UDP over port 135.
Next we have NetBIOS and it's used
to conduct name querying,
sending of data and other functions
over a NetBIOS connection.
This operates over three ports,
137, 138 and 139
using both TCP and UDP.
IMAP or the Internet
Message Access Protocol
is used to receive
email from a mail server
with more features than
your POP3 servers do.
It's going to operate over port 143
using TCP when unencrypted.
Now, we'll talk
about the encrypted version later on.
SNMP is the Simple Network
Management Protocol.
It's used to remotely
monitor network devices
using a UDP connection over port 161.
Now we go to 162,
this is the port reserved for SNMPTRAP.
This is used to send
Trap and InformRequests
to the SNMP Manager on a network
using both TCP and UDP connections.
Next we have LDAP or the
Lightweight Directory Access Protocol.
It's used to maintain directories of users
and other objects.
If you're using Active Directory
inside a Windows environment this relies
on LDAP to function.
LDAP will use port 389 over both TCP
and UDP connections.
We'll talk about its
encrypted variate later on.
Next we have HTTPS
or the Hyper Text Transfer Protocol Secure
which is what you're using
to watch this course right now.
It's used to transmit
web pages to a client
over an SSL or TLS encrypted connection.
Essentially, this is
the same thing as HTTP
over port 80 except it's going to use
an encrypted tunnel to
secure that information
and make sure nobody can see it.
This is going to ensure
confidentiality for us.
HTTPS uses port 443 and a TCP connection.
Next we have the Server
Message Block or SMB
and it's used to provide
shared access to files
and other resources over a network.
It's going to operate on port 445
using a TCP connection.
Earlier we talked about SMTP,
the Simple Mail Transfer Protocol.
But now we're going to talk
about the secure version of it,
the Simple Mail Transfer
Protocol over SSL or TLS.
This is going to be used to send email
over the Internet inside
of an encrypted tunnel
to make sure you maintain confidentiality.
This is going to use one of two ports,
either 465 or 587 and it's going to use it
over a TCP connection.
Just like we had HTTP and HTTPS,
this is the same thing
with SMTP and SMTP Secure.
Now, Syslog is going to be used
to conduct computer message logging,
especially for routers and firewall logs.
It operates over port 514 using UDP.
LDAP over SSL or TLS
operates over port 636
using either TCP or UDP.
Again, LDAP is used to
maintain directories
of users and other objects
over an encrypted SSL
or TLS connection and it's
simply the secure version
of LDAP and Active Directory.
Next we have iSCSI.
iSCSI is used
for linking data storage
facilities over IP.
This is commonly used in
storage area networks.
iSCSI is going to operate on port 860
and it's using TCP.
Next we have File Transfer
Protocol Secure or FTPS.
This is used to transfer
files from host to host
over an encrypted connection.
By default FTP doesn't
provide any encryption
and it sends everything in the clear.
But with FTPS going over port 989 and 990,
this is going to give us a TCP connection
that is secured with an encryption tunnel
and this is going to
make it much more secure
for us to send our files.
Our next secure variant is for IMAP.
If you remember,
IMAP is the Internet
Message Access Protocol
and it's used to receive
email from a mail server.
But this time we're going
to do it over an SSL
or TLS encrypted connection.
When we do that we're going
to use port 993 using TCP.
Next we have the secure version of POP3
which again, is used to receive email
from a mail server using an SSL
or TLS encrypted connection.
This is going to provide
us better confidentiality
by ensuring everything is encrypted.
It's going to operate
over port 995 over TCP.
Next I have port 1433 which is used
by the Microsoft SQL server
to receive SQL database
queries from its clients.
This is going to use a TCP connection.
Then we have RADIUS
which is the Remote Authentication Dial-In
User Service and it's
used for authentication
and authorization over port 1645
and accounting over port 1646.
Now, these two ports are an alternative
to its standard ports of 1812 and 1813.
RADIUS operates using UDP.
Next we're going to talk about L2TP
which is our first VPN related protocol.
L2TP operates over port 1701 using UDP.
L2TP stands for the Layer
2 Tunneling Protocol
and is used as an underlying VPN protocol
but has no inherent security.
Because of this if you use L2TP you need
to make sure that you're pairing it
with IPsec to ensure
you have good security.
Another protocol when we deal with VPNs
is called the PPTP,
the Point-to-Point Tunneling Protocol.
It's another underlying VPN protocol
but this one,
unlike L2TP, has built-in security.
PPTP operates over port 1723
using both TCP and UDP connections.
Now, a few slides ago
we talked about RADIUS
and we said that it
used ports 1645 and 1646
as its alternate ports.
Well, its defaults are 1812 and 1813
as you can see now.
This is just a reminder that RADIUS
is going to use these ports over UDP,
just like we talked about before.
FCIP or the Fibre Channel IP is used
to encapsulate Fibre Channel frames
within TCP/IP packets.
This is usually used
for storage area networks as well.
Now, FCIP operates over port 3225
over both TCP and UDP.
Earlier in this lesson
we talked about iSCSI.
But we're going to return to it now
to cover the Target side of it.
iSCSI Target is a listening port
for iSCSI targeted devices
when they're linking
data storage facilities over IP.
It's going to operate
on port 3260 over TCP.
Next we have RDP,
the Remote Desktop Protocol which is used
to remotely view and control
other Windows systems
via a graphical User Interface.
It does this over port 3389
using both TCP and UDP.
Now, be careful with this one
because it's 3389 for RDP
but 389 for LDAP and a
lot of times students
will get those two confused.
Next we have Diameter
which is a more advanced
AAA protocol than RADIUS
and it serves as a replacement for RADIUS.
It also operates over port 3868
and it uses TCP as its
connection mechanism.
Next we have a Syslog over TLS connection
which is going to be used
to conduct computer message logging,
especially for routers and firewalls
over a TLS encrypted connection.
Syslog over TLS operates
on port 6514 using TCP.
Now, I know that was a lot of information
in a very short amount of time.
After watching this video once
I know you don't have all
those ports memorized.
I recommend making a
list and testing yourself
over and over again on these ports.
This is critical information
to answer a lot of questions on the exam,
either directly or indirectly.
Remember, you can rewatch this video
as many times as you like.
And our study notes we
gave you at the beginning
of this course have all the information
from these slides included in it.
Now, with that being said,
I do recommend you make
flashcards with the protocol
on one side and the
ports and the connection
on the other side,
and use that to test yourself
and aid in your memorization.
For example, if you have
one side that has HTTP,
the other side should have port 80, TCP.
Take time to learn these
ports and protocols
for the exam.
I promise you,
your time is spent very well here
and you're going to be
rewarded on test day.