- Securing network media.
Network media is the cabling
that makes up our network.
This can be copper,
fiber optic, or coaxial.
And they're going to be
used as a connectivity
method inside of our wired networks.
Now, in addition to all the
cables there's other parts
of the cabling plant
we have to think about.
All those intermediate devices
like patch panels, punch-down blocks,
and network jacks all
make up this cabling plant
that runs throughout our organization.
And each part of that can
be a vulnerability for us.
The first vulnerability
I want to discuss is EMI.
This stands for
electromagnetic interference.
Electromagnetic interference
is a disturbance
that can affect electrical circuits,
devices, and cables due to radiation
or electromagnetic conduction that occurs.
Now, EMI is something
that happens normally
inside our businesses
and inside our homes.
EMI is caused by all sorts
of things, like televisions,
microwaves, cordless
phones, baby monitors,
motors like inside your
vacuum, and other devices.
Anything that is really a powered device,
even handheld drills can cause
electromagnetic interference.
Now, to minimize EMI you
need to install shielding
around the source, for instance,
your air conditioner
lets off a lot of EMI.
You could put shielding around that.
Or you can shield the cable itself
by choosing shielded twisted-pair.
Now, STP cables, or shielded twisted-pair,
have foil around either each
twisted-pair in the cable
or around the entire
bundle of twisted-pairs
to prevent emanations out of the cable
or interference entering into the cable.
STP gives you double benefit, it keeps
things out, and it keeps things in.
This is good for security and helps
minimize this vulnerability.
Now, the next vulnerability we have
is called radio frequency
interference, or RFI.
RFI is just another type
of interference like EMI.
Like EMI it's a
disturbance that can affect
your electrical circuits,
your devices, and your cables.
But instead of being caused by electrical
waves it's caused by radio waves.
Most often from AM and FM transmission
towers or cellular phone towers.
Now, cell towers and radio
towers near your office
can be a big source of RFI
in your wireless networks.
And when you have a
significant amount of RFI
this can cause to network
connectivity problems
for your wired networks, as well
as disturbing your wireless networks too.
Now, this is something that
you're going to have to address.
And a lot of it is going to be addressed
by shielding the building
or getting stronger devices
that can overcome the radio frequency
interference that's occurring.
Another vulnerability we have
is what's known as crosstalk.
Crosstalk occurs when
a signal is transmitted
on one copper wire, and it creates
an undesired effect on
another copper wire.
So, when we think about
having two copper wires,
like inside of a twisted-pair cable,
if the shielding inside that protects
those wires comes off,
then we can actually
have crossover from one wire to another.
And that causes interference because
of the data emanations and EMI.
Crosstalk is essentially that,
but in very close proximity.
Now, this becomes very common with older
cable network types,
things like Cat3 networks,
or even some early Cat5 networks.
Most of our Cat5E and Cat6A networks
aren't really subject to
crosstalk nearly as much.
Another place is see
crosstalk happen a lot
is if you have punch-down blocks,
and you decide to use an older terminal,
like the old 66 blocks that
were used for phone lines,
and tried to use that for networks.
Networks should always use a 110 block,
like you learned back in
Network+ and A+ because it gives
more spacing and prevents
crosstalk from occurring.
The next thing you want to
talk about here is STP cables
because STP cables are really
helpful to our networks.
They can prevent some of that
RFI, they can prevent EMI.
And they can help with crosstalk.
If you use those individual
shielded twisted-pair cables
it's really going to help eliminate
crosstalk altogether for you.
Unfortunately, though, most
organizations don't use STP.
They still use unshielded
twisted-pair cabling.
The reason is it's a lot
cheaper and easier to work with.
Because of this you're going to see a lot
of organizations favor UTP cabling
as opposed to STP cabling.
Because, again, the cost is
about 50% higher to use STP.
Now data emanations is another
issue we have to think about.
When we talked about EMI we
were talking about things
trying to get into our
network and causing issues.
Well, data emanation is the opposite.
It comes from inside your cable,
and it starts generating
a field around that cable
that when you're transmitting information
over the network could be picked up
by somebody who's trying to capture that.
This is things on your
network trying to escape.
So, if somebody is nearby
they can actually capture
those data emanations,
and they could reconstruct
that data that was
traveling over your network.
This is kind of paranoid
level stuff here, right?
And you probably aren't
going to deal with this much
in your organization,
unless you're a contractor
for something like the
military or the government
who holds really valuable information,
and they have these top secret
military defensive plans,
that's when you have to start thinking
about data emanations as a real threat.
So if you're like most people,
and you're working for a corporation,
though, you're probably not nearly
as worried about data emanations.
But something else the attackers can do
is tap into your communications doing
it locally using physical connections.
Now, what do I mean by this?
Well, if they can get
physical access to your space,
and get into your network closet,
and touch your punch-down panel,
they could actually tap into it there
and get a copy of the network traffic.
For example, this was very
common with phone networks.
If as an attacker I could
get into your office building
and find your patch panel I could use
a telephone technician's butt
set like the one shown here,
and attach it to the patch panel,
and listen to all of the phone
calls that were being made.
Now, if you're trying to
tap into the network itself
the easiest thing to do here is to find
an RJ45 port somewhere in the building.
Once you get into the
building, and you've gotten
into one of those jacks,
you can plug your laptop in.
And if they're not using MAC filtering
you're already connected.
If they are using MAC
filtering you're going to have
to bypass that, but that's
not too hard to do either.
Now, to prevent this
you want to use things
like Network Access Control,
and some other things
like network segmentation and VLANs.
So if an attacker does
get onto your network
they're stuck into one corner of it,
and they can't spread out
across the whole thing.
Now, if you can't find an open jack,
but you still want to collect things
completely passively, you can do this
by splitting the wires of
a twisted-pair connection.
You can open up the cable in
an area that nobody is seeing.
You can cut the wire and
solder on additional wires
to each of the twisted-pair's
internal cables.
This will give you a copy of
the data and you can plug it
back in and give the
network a copy of the data.
This lets you capture
the data as it transmits
back and forth over the network
completely passively, and
no one's going to see it.
But, again, you've got to get
physical access to the network
and get close enough
to be able to do this.
Now, I mentioned data emanations earlier,
but we really didn't talk
about how you can capture them.
To capture them you'll
use a spectrum analyzer.
This is going to capture
all of the radio frequencies
that are openly available in the area.
You can then dial it in for
that particular network itself
and dump that amount of radio frequency
into a program that will convert it
back to the ones and
zeroes of the network.
Load that into a packet
analyzer like Wireshark,
and you now have data from the network.
To prevent data emanations from happening
you should switch your
networks to fiber optic cables
because they don't have
any emanation at all.
Because fiber optic cables work with light
instead of electricity
there's no radiation
outside of the cable,
and they're not affected
by EMI or radio frequency either.
Now, are fiber optic
cables completely safe?
Well, no, of course not because
attackers are smart people.
And they always come up with creative
ways of bypassing security.
In fact, they've created what's called
a fiber optic splitter, where
they can attach the device
to a fiber port on one
side, and get two copies
of every piece of
communication, one that will go
into their machine, and one
that will go into your network.
That way you don't even
know they're there.
And it's a completely passive
way to tap the network.
So, how do we prevent all of these
type of issues from happening?
Well, you may have noticed that most
of these attacks are
occurring by the person
physically touching the network to tap it.
To prevent this you can install
a protected distribution system, or a PDS.
A PDS is a secured system of
cable management to ensure
that the wired network remains
free from eavesdropping,
tapping, data emanations,
and other threats.
They are kind of expensive, though,
because they add locks
to every network closet.
They enclose every cable
distribution point.
And they run cables
through a protected conduit
that runs throughout the ceiling.
Because of this expense I've
only really seen this used
in very large organizations
that are really worried
about security, government
buildings, or the military.
Most small businesses and
most medium-sized businesses
aren't going to use a
protected distribution system.
Now, I know we covered
a lot in this lesson.
And the exam isn't going to focus on much
of the information we covered,
so don't worry too much.
Now, I just wanted to expose you
to all these concepts to
ensure that you've heard it
at least once during your studies.
The biggest questions you're
going to see on the exam
from this lesson are going
to be about EMI, RFI,
and the concept of wire tapping a network.
That said, in the real
world you do need to think
about these things from an
attacker's point of view,
so you can determine what is a real threat
that you should put money against,
and what you can decide
is an unlikely risk.
And you're going to just
accept it the way it is,
and not spend money to mitigate it.
(instrumental music)