- Every encryption cipher
is attempting to do
one basic function.
We're trying to assure you
that confidentiality exists
in the data they've encrypted.
But, no encryption cipher
is truly unbreakable.
Given enough time and
computer processing power
any encryption can be defeated,
including AES, DES and
many others, eventually.
Well, that is all of them except one.
This is called a One-Time Pad.
Now, a One-Time Pad is a stream cipher
that encrypts plaintext information
with a secret random key
that is the same length
as the plaintext input.
This secret random key
is knows as a keystream
and it's comprised of a
series of random bits.
If the keystream is truly random,
the only way an attacker
could decrypt the information
back to the plaintext
is if they had access
to that randomly created keystream.
To describe how this works a little bit,
let's do a lo-tech version of this.
Let's say that you and
I both wanted to come up
with a secret code so that we can
transmit information to each other
and nobody else in the world
would be able to know it.
The way we can do this is
by using a One-Time Pad.
We'll each buy a thousand-page
notebook and on every page,
we're going to put a
number on there, at random.
And your book and my
book are going to match.
So, for everyone of those thousand pages,
there's a random number on it.
So, now every time we want to
send a message to each other,
we're going to perform
a rotation cipher on it.
And so, if I wanted to send
you the word "Hi", H-I,
then I'm going to rotate the h
by the number on the
first page, which is 3.
So instead of h, it would be h, i, j, k.
So I'd put a k down.
And then I would rotate the i,
the second letter in my word,
based on the second page of our notebook,
in this case, zero.
So now I'm going to have K-I,
and send you that message.
Because you have the same notebook,
you can then subtract
three from the k to get h,
and zero from the i to get i,
and you know the message is "Hi".
But anybody else in the world,
wouldn't be able to know what it was.
Now once we use those
pages, we rip them out,
we burn them, and we never use them again.
Because this is truly a random key string,
and no one would be able
to decrypt our messages
if they don't have that
random number string
written down like we do.
The reason is, there was no
real mathematical formula
or pattern to determine here.
If I use the same number
for the entire message,
we can use cryptoanalysis and figure out
that all of the letters will move
by five, or 10, or 13,
but by changing every single number,
or in the data stream, every single bit,
there's no pattern.
So they're only going to be
able to decode that message
if they're able to get a copy
of our one-time use pads.
Now there is one problem
with a one-time pad though,
and it's that there is not such thing
as a truly random sequence of numbers
if those numbers are
created by a computer.
Computer aren't random.
They're based on math and algorithms.
And so, computers can't simply create
purely random numbers.
Instead, they try to simulate
it, using algorithms,
and they try to create what's known
as a Pseudo-Random Number
Generator, or PRNG.
This is an algorithm that
spits out what looks,
to you and me, like random numbers,
but to other computers,
they can figure out
what the initial seed was
and then that takes away the randomness.
These numbers are used
for a variety of purposes,
including encryption, as
well as game development
and other things that you
might need a random number for.
For example, you may wish
to have images uploaded
by your users and assign a random filename
made out of a series of numbers.
In truth, though, the
numbers aren't purely random,
because computer create them based
on mathematical functions.
Or, you may need to generate
a unique session key
to identify a user, and this would be
an appropriate place to
use a pseudo-random number.
But, if someone can
figure out the sequence
of pseudo-random numbers you're using,
they can guess the next session,
and do a session hijack.
Going back to our
one-time use pad, though,
if we could create the truly
random sequence of numbers
then we could securely exchange
the information contained
in that one-time use pad
and then we would have
a truly unbreakable encryption cipher.
Unfortunately, though,
we don't have a truly
random sequence of numbers
that we can rely on.
So one-time pads aren't often used.
Instead, we use the concept
on one-time use passwords.
You've seen this discussed inside
our multi-fact authentication lesson.
For example, you could use a random number
that's texted to you by your website
whenever you attempt to log in.
Or, you might have an RSA secure token
that displays pseudo-random numbers
that you use to prove you have possession
of that token as your second
fact of authentication.
These are two good
examples of where we use
pseudo-random numbers in
the security of our network.