- In this lesson I'm going to
demonstrate how to conduct an
initialization vector attack on a
WEP protected access point.
As I said before, WEP is
extremely insecure because
it only uses a 24 bit
initialization vector.
Regardless of what key you
choose, this attack is going to
work every single time.
This is the reason that I say
you never, ever want to use
WEP in your networks.
If you find a network using
WEP in your organization,
you should immediately work
to upgrade it to WPA2 instead.
Let's jump into the lab
and I'll show you exactly
how this works.
So the first thing we're going
to do is where you're going to
start with airodump-ng and
then the card that we have
which is wlan0mon.
And notice it's starting
to scan for that particular
network that we're looking for.
In our case, we already found
it, it is wireless hacking.
This WEP network right here.
And this is the BSSID, or the
Mac address for that network.
So, for us to attack it, we are
going to use airodump-ng again.
And in this case we are
going to specifically tell it
which channel we want to go
after, which is channel one,
right here, from the
wireless hacking network.
We want to go after the
BSSID that was provided
for that network, and we want to go ahead
and write that data to a
file which is going to be
wireless hacking dump, is what
we're going to call that file.
And then we're going to
give it the card itself,
which is wlan0mon, and
hit enter, and off it goes
starting to scan the
network, which is helpful.
But we're not quite there yet.
Notice the data packets are
climbing, but we haven't yet
associated ourself to that
network to be able to start
doing things like packet
injection and capturing those
initialization vectors.
So I'm going to go ahead and
put this up here to make some
extra room and we'll just
bring that right across the top
and let it continue to run.
We're going to open up a new
terminal and I'm going to bring that
down here to the bottom.
Now, in the new terminal what
I need to do is I need to
start doing a authentication
to the network using
fake authentication, which is
our first step in the hack.
So, that first step in the
hack is that we are going to do
a program called aireplay,
and in aireplay-ng,
we are going to use
fakeauth as our command,
zero for infinite attempts,
dash a and the Mac address
that we are going after,
which again we still
have pasted right there.
And then we're going to use
the Mac address that we are
coming from, which we
have to find ourself.
So we are going to open
up another terminal,
can see how you start getting
quite a few terminals,
and just type in something like ifconfig.
When you do that, you're
going to get the Mac address
for wlan0mon, and the first
12 digits here is that
Mac address for our network card.
So I'm just going to copy that
and then we can paste that in.
Now, this use dashes, but
for this particular command
you have to use colons, so
I'm going to arrow through
and change those to
colons, as you can see.
And the command's not done yet,
'cause what's the one thing
we haven't told it?
We haven't told it which card to use.
So we have to use wlan0mon,
and then we will hit enter,
and off it goes sending a authentication.
We not have an authentication
made with this network.
So we can move into the
second phase of our attack,
which is going to be the packet injection.
So, for the packet injection
we are going to still use
the aireplay command.
Most of it is going to be the
same, so what I'm going to do
instead of typing it
all is hit the up arrow,
which will bring back
the last command I used.
The big differences here
is we are not going to use
fake authentication anymore.
Instead, we want to use an
arpreplay so that we can create
additional traffic on this network.
Instead of a for the access point,
we're going to use b for the
access point which tells
it that's the base station.
We're still going to use the
card that we're coming from
and the network card wlan0mon.
When we hit enter, off it
goes, and notice that we have
a couple of arp packets
here, and our data is
going to start going up.
We have a lot of frame loss.
Once you have a couple
of arp requests that have
been successful, you can hit
Control + c and stop that.
Now, with this attack,
it does help if this
is a busy network.
Right now, as we're doing
this, you can see the
data packets are going up.
The reason those data packets
are going up is because
I'm streaming YouTube on the
device, this base station here,
which this client, which is
my iPhone, is talking to this
access point and streaming
YouTube, which is collecting
a lot of data.
Now, the next thing you want
to do is start cracking.
Every 5,000 data packets that
go up, it will start trying
to do another attempt.
It's really easy, you just
use aircrack-ng, and then the
file name of what you're
going to be using.
Let me clear the screen here,
and the file that I'm going to
be using is wirelesshackingdump-02.cap.
The reason it's the second
one's 'cause I've run this
attempt once before showing you.
So, all we're going to use
is aircrack-ng and then the
file name that you're
going after, and hit enter.
Off it goes, starting to crack away.
Right now it already has
14,000 initialization vectors
collected, and you can see
that here from the data,
but that wasn't enough.
So when this hits 15,000, you're
going to see this kick off
again without me doing
anything, and we'll see if we
can crack that key.
So here it goes again.
It's going off and testing
the different keys.
And it didn't find it.
So it'll try again at 20,000.
Generally, it's going to
find it somewhere between
10,000 and 25,000.
It really depends on where
that particular key is inside
the key space, depending
on what that hexadecimal
password was that we used.
So again, you can see the
data packets climbing up
as I'm streaming different YouTube videos.
Every time I start another video it starts
downloading all that data.
All those frames have an
initialization vector in there,
and they're able to be
captured so that we can
start seeing that information.
So now we have over 20,000.
It's going to try again and there it is.
It found our key.
17, 25, 83, A-E-F-A.
So, we now have a key.
What are we going to do with it?
Well, the next thing we want
to do is we want to see if that
key actually works and be
able to get onto a network.
We can do that through
Kali or we can do it
through your Windows
machine or your Mac machine,
it depends on what
you're ultimate goal is.
For this example, I'm going
to show you how to use it
inside your Macintosh machine.
You can do the same thing in
Windows, and again in Kali.
If we can cancel this
capturing at this point,
so we'll hit Control + c, and
we're going to switch back
to our client machine,
in my case Macintosh.
So now that we're back
on our Windows or our
Macintosh machine, you'll connect to that
wireless network just
like you normally do.
So we're going to go down to
wireless hacking, and it's
going to ask us for the passcode.
My passcode that we just
cracked was 17, 25, 83, A-E-F-A,
and if I go ahead and join,
we should see if I can pull
an IP address from this network.
And if we look at it, you can
see here we did pull and IP
address from this network,
and we are connected to that
access point starting
with c8 a7, that BSSID,
which is the one for wireless hacking.
So, our hack did work
and it was successful.
(techno music)