- Securing applications.
By far the most commonly
used productivity suite
in the world is Microsoft Office.
This includes Word for word processing,
Excel for Spreadsheets,
PowerPoint for slide presentation,
Outlook for email, and many others.
Now, how can we protect the
applications themselves,
and the files that they create?
Well, that's what we're going
to cover in this lesson.
First, let's talk about the obvious.
If you have a document and you
want to protect its content,
you should use a password to do it.
It's a really simple built in feature
across the Office suite.
To create a password to
protect your files from
modification, or even being viewed,
you can do this using the password protect
feature under the tools menu bar option.
As shown here on the
screen, this is an example
from Microsoft Word, but it works in Word,
Excel and PowerPoint.
Also, your files can be set
to read only if you desire.
This will prevent any of your contents
from being modified by unauthorized users.
Another thing you want to think about
when it comes to security is macros.
And we talked about that a bit back
when we talked about macro viruses.
You want to make sure you
check your macro settings.
You can find this under your preferences
or your tools options, and
then going to the security tab.
By default, you should
want to disable macros,
with or without notification.
This will increase the
security of your organization.
Now, when it's installed
originally by Microsoft,
macros are enabled, so
you want to take the time
to disable this in your baseline image.
Most organizations are
going to decide to disable
macros completely and
not even give their user
an option to be able to enable them.
To do this, you can set that
through your group policy
inside the Windows
server and push that out
to all of your clients.
Another way to secure your information
is to use digital certificates.
If your organization is already
using digital certificates
as part of its organizational security,
you should enable your
documents to be locked down
and only be opened by
the person presenting
a valid digital certificate.
This again is another option that you can
find inside of Word.
Additionally, you want to think about how
you're going to encrypt your documents
to protect their contents.
This can be done within
the Microsoft Office
products themselves, or you can use
the underlying system capabilities,
something like Bitlocker to Go.
So at this point, we have
some pretty secure files.
We've disabled our macros, we've password
protected them and we've encrypted them.
Let's go and shift our focus
over to email for a moment.
Inside the Microsoft Office suite,
there's a program called MS Outlook.
Microsoft Outlook is used for email
and if you embed your digital signatures
and digital certificate configurations
into Microsoft Outlook, you can have
increased email security.
This relies on a PKI or
public key infrastructure.
We'll talk about that when we get
into the cryptography section
of this course later on.
Now, another thing when we start talking
about Microsoft Outlook is that our emails
start getting to be
overwhelming sometimes,
and we have to start saving
space by archiving them off.
In Microsoft Outlook, the way we do this
is by archiving them to a PST file.
Now, this PST file though should be
encrypted or password protected if you're
going to to store it on
a large network share,
like a shared drive.
I see this a lot in organizations
where they'll only give
you a certain amount
of space on the email server.
Some people will archive
their files off into the PST
and then put that onto the shared drive.
If you're going to do
that, password protect it
and encrypt it for your
own safety and precaution.
Another concern we have when we deal
with email is spam and junk mail.
And you can get a lot of this.
If you want to start
removing a lot of that,
you should set up rules that will end up
filtering out that spam
both on your exchange server
as well as on your personal computer.
Again, Microsoft Outlook
will allow you to do this
on your application side
or Microsoft Exchange
will allow you to do
it on the server side.
So as we start wrapping up this lesson,
let's start talking about what you can do
to help protect yourself
from rogue applications.
Now this is going to move beyond
the Microsoft Office suite,
and into every other
application out there.
There's one key tool inside of Windows
that helps protect you.
It's called the User Account Control.
UAC is a security
component of Windows Vista
and newer operating systems
that keeps every user,
besides your actual administrator account
in a standard user mode.
And this way, when you
try to run a program,
it's going to ask you
if you want to be run
as an administrator and if so,
you need to put in the
administrator credentials.
So when you think about UAC
or User Account Control,
just think about the fact that it's going
to prevent unauthorized access
and avoid user error in the
form of accidental changes,
because it's running
everything as a standard user,
as opposed to running
it as an administrator.
Now in the next lesson,
I'm going to show you
how we can white list and
black list applications.
To keep any applications off your system,
that you don't want running
and allowing those that you do to be run.