- Symptoms of Infection.
How do you know your computer
has been infected with malware?
Well, the most common thing is to notice
that it starts beginning to act strange.
That could be a myriad of
different things, though.
For example, your computer
might start running
slower than normal.
Why might this occur?
Well, if you have a worm for example,
it's using up processor
resources and network resources
to spread itself throughout the system
and throughout the network.
If you happen to be getting spam,
that again is something that's
going to tax your system.
Lots of different malware will
start making your computer
act slower than normal.
And this is one of the indications
that you have a problem.
Another symptom of infection
is that your computer starts locking up
or stops responding to you frequently.
Maybe you're seeing more
'blue screens of death'
than you've ever seen before.
Well, this again is something
that is a common symptom of malware.
If a virus goes in and
overwrites a critical system file
by mistake, that can cause the
computer to crash or lock up.
This brings us to our third thing.
If your computer restarts
or crashes a lot,
this again is another
symptom that you may have
a malware infection.
Next, if your hard drive,
files or applications
aren't accessible anymore,
this could be a symptom
of a malware infection.
Because if a virus or piece
of malware takes over a file,
it's going to change its permissions.
And by doing that, it can
remove your permissions
that allow you to run it
or delete it or change it.
This is one of the ways
that the malware will keep
persistence in your system.
Another symptom of malware
is if your computer starts
to make strange noises,
or you start to see
unusual error messages,
or your computer, the display
starts looking strange,
or when you print something,
it looks like gibberish or gobbledygook,
and it uses symbols
instead of normal letters.
All of these things can happen
when you get a virus or you get malware,
depending on the way the virus or malware
starts infecting your system.
Another sign that you
might have an infection
is if you start to see new
icons appear on your desktop
or conversely, icons from your
desktop start to disappear.
Again, as any additional
programs are added,
new icons might show up, and
if you start deleting programs,
that can remove those as well.
Another way that malware
tries to hide itself
when it's in your system is by
using double file extensions.
This is because in Windows, by default,
if there's a know file extension,
such as .exe for executable,
or .txt for text files,
that part won't be shown
on the icon's name.
So if you have something that says
textfile.txt on your desktop,
it could have a hidden
.exe at the end of it.
And when you double-click that file
that looks like a text file,
it's actually going to
run this executable file.
And that can actually embed malware
into your system even further.
Another symptom that you may
have had something bad happen
is if you try to run
your antivirus software
but it just won't run.
A lot of malware is programmed
to attack your antivirus software,
and that way it can
prevent it from running
and maintain persistence longer.
The reason for this is that malware
doesn't want to be taken
out of your system.
And if you're able to run your antivirus
you might be able to clean up the malware.
But if they can attack your antivirus
and keep it from running,
that means that they can
stay on your computer for
longer and dig in deeper.
Yet another symptom is
when your files or folders
are corrupted, or you may
see new files and folders
that have been created.
Again, as a piece of malware
goes and infects your files
this corruption can make them be deleted,
or it'll create new
files for it to hide in.
Again, the malware might do this as a way
to maintain persistence and
dig in deeper into your system.
And this can add new
files that get infected
and those files might be
put across the network.
The final symptom is if you try to go
and use your system restore
function within Windows
and you can't do it.
Because again, similarly
to what I talked about
with antivirus being
turned off by malware,
malware is going to try to
turn off your system restore,
because they don't want
you to be able to go back
and restore from a known good backup.
In this way, malware again
is trying to maintain that persistence.
All of these things are
really summarized quite simply
with one simple statement.
If your computer is
acting funny or strange
you may be infected with malware
and so it's best to boot up into safe mode
or boot from an external drive
and then scan your computer
with a good antivirus software.
(soft techno music)