- In this demonstration,
I'm going to show you
how a null session is created.
But you may be wondering,
what exactly is a null session?
Well, a null session
is a connection to the
Windows interprocess communications share
known as the IPC dollar sign.
This is an administrative
share that you don't see
as a normal user, but it allows computers
across the network to send
information that they know
about files, folders,
users, groups, computers
and servers to each other.
Now, as an attacker, if
you're able to create
a null connection to a
computer, you can use that
as part of your information gathering
and enumeration and be able
to use all of that data
as part of your follow on attack.
So if a null connection
can give you access to all
of this information,
how easy is it to really
get a null connection set up?
Well you can do it with one line of code
inside the command line.
As I'm going to show you here,
using my Windows 10 machine,
over a local area network.
So here I am at the command prompt.
To do a null connection,
all you have to use
is the net use command.
Net space use and then the ip address
that you want to connect to.
In my case, that's 10.0.2.15
and then slash ipc$
to connect to that administrative share
the inner process communication.
Now, from there you're going
to use a space, two quotes,
which is going to say
that you have no password,
the slash u for the user
and then two more quotes,
which says you have no user.
It's a blank user and a blank password.
If you hit enter, now that
you have this connection,
you can start gathering
information such as the users
and the groups, the files, the
shares, the local resources,
all of that using other tools
that a penetration tester
or hacker might use.
So now that you've seen
how easy it is to create
a null connection, you may be wondering,
what can I do to stop this
from being used against me?
Well, for one, on your
local machine if you block
port 445 and 139, this
is going to block smb,
your file sharing, as
well as port 139 net bios
and both of these ports
are used heavily to
get information from your
machine and do things
like enumeration such as when you're
using the null session.
So this will be your first
step in blocking someone
from getting there.
The second thing you can
do, is you can install
an IPS at your boundary.
This will prevent anyone
from outside your network
trying to make a null connection
in to any of your machines.
Both of these are good steps
in limiting the ability
of an attacker to be able
to gather information
about you and your network.