- SIM cloning, and ID theft.
If you've gone and bought
a new cell phone recently,
you've gone to the store,
they've pulled out a little
chip out of your phone,
and placed it into your new phone.
What is that chip?
Well, that's a SIM card.
It stands for Subscriber Identity Module.
This is an integrated
circuit that securely stores
the international mobile
subscriber identity,
your IMSI number and its related key.
This is what tells the cellphone towers
which device is assigned to which number.
Now, if someone is able
to clone your SIM card,
they can pretend they're you.
This was very popular in
the early days of cellphones
because if I could pretend that I was you,
I could rack up lots
of long-distance calls
and lots of minutes used on cellular,
and not get charged for 'em
because, you would get charged for 'em.
And so people would go
through and impersonate you
and they would do this
by cloning your SIM card.
Now SIM cloning allows two cell phones
to utilize the same service
and allows the attacker to gain access
to the phone's personal data.
So if I'm cloning your SIM card
the towers think I'm you.
So when somebody sends you a text message,
I get a copy and you get a copy.
And so now I'm able to keep
track of what you're getting.
Now this is very dangerous for you,
the good news is that
SIM has changed it's ways
over the years.
The first versions of SIM cards
were very easy to clone,
but the newer SIM version two cards
are much much harder.
So this gives us a lot more security.
Now one of the second problems
we have with mobile phones
and SIM cards and phone numbers,
is when people try to
take over your phone.
And so you may think alright, great,
SIM card cloning is almost
a thing of the past,
version two has taken care of it.
Well, attackers are smart,
and they find other ways to
hijack your cell phone account.
What they started doing now
is they will call up
your cell phone provider
and pretend to be you.
This is a social engineering scheme.
They'll say I just bought a new phone
and I need to get it activated.
And the nice customer
service agent will ask them
some basic questions about themselves,
like maybe their date of birth,
where they went to high school,
their name and address,
things that you can usually find online.
So the attacker pretends to be you
and gives that information,
the customer service agent
is wonderfully helpful,
and they transfer your phone service
from you to the attacker.
Now the attacker has a phone
and a new SIM card that is
now attached to your number.
Why are they doing this?
Why do they want your phone number?
Well, it comes down to
two step authentication.
A lot of websites now are using
two factor authentication.
Where you log in and then
they send you a text message
with a secret code
that you then put into
the website to verify
you are who you say your are.
If the attacker is able to
take over your phone number,
they can now pretend to be you
and log into your bank,
your Facebook, your Gmail,
or whatever else you have
for two factor authentication.
This is becoming a big problem,
and so you have to be careful
where you post your phone number.
Because if somebody now
has your phone number,
and they've already stolen your account,
your email and maybe your password,
they can now take over your phone number
and then take over your accounts.
So this is what we call ID
theft, or account takeover.
So, how do we combat this?
Well, one of the ways is to be careful
where you post your phone number.
Because if you are a
victim of a data breach
and somebody has stolen
your name and your address
and your email,
and now they have your phone number,
they can perform this
account takeover against you,
and now they're going to be
able to log into your accounts
as if they were you,
even if you had the two
factor authentication set up.
So, what do we recommend to bypass this
if you really want to be paranoid?
Well, you can go and get
a google voice number
or something of that nature.
Where you have a single phone
number that people call,
and then nobody knows your
actual cell phone number
that's behind it.
You then can use that cell phone number
to validate your accounts for
two factor authentication.
Again, this is getting a little paranoid
but this is something that
some people are worried about
and are taking this action
and these steps to bypass it.