- Backdoors and logic bombs.
A backdoor was originally
placed in computer programs
to bypass the normal security
and authentication functions.
Now, if this sounds like
a horrible idea to you,
it really is, and it's a
horrible security practice.
This is something that
was originally created
back in the 80's, by
manufacturers and programmers
as a way for them to
get back into the system
to do maintenance and repairs,
without having to go through
all the authentications
and going through the firewalls
and the layers of security that they would
if they went in the front door.
Now, this is a horrible and bad practice,
and it should not be
used in current networks.
And these days, it's
actually considered a breach
of good, secure coding practices.
But, back in the 80's and the 90's,
and even into the early 2000's,
backdoors were a commonplace thing
that were put in by programmers.
Now these days, most software
does not have a backdoor.
It's been patched up and cleared up
because they know how bad
these are for security.
But, there is something that
acts just like a backdoor.
What do you think that might be?
Well, it's a remote access trojan.
A remote access trojan can
be placed by an attacker
to maintain their persistent
access to your system.
So if I'm able to trick you into clicking
a spearfishing link, and
then you install malware
based on clicking that link,
now I have something that
can make a call back to me.
That can give me that remote access.
I have a way to bypass your
system's natural security
and use that remote access trojan
as a backdoor, to gain
access to your system
anytime I want.
Another insecure coding
practice that was used by
programmers is what we
refer to as an Easter Egg.
An Easter Egg would be
placed in the code as a joke
or a form of gag gift.
Essentially, there would
be different things
that would happen in
different video games,
or different pieces of software
when certain code was executed.
For example, a few years ago,
you could go to Google.com
and type in do a barrel roll,
and the whole page would
do a 360 degree rotation
as if it was doing a
barrel roll in an airplane.
There was no real function to doing that
except it was a joke, it was a gag.
It was a joke that Google
programmers decided
to put into the code.
That's a form of an Easter Egg.
Now, Easter Eggs are generally harmless
but they do add additional code,
that can have additional vulnerabilities.
The reason for this is because their code,
because it's a joke, is usually
put in at the last minute
and it doesn't undergo
rigorous security testing.
Now, why am I talking about
Easter Eggs in this lesson?
Well, it's because it brings us up
to the subject of logic bombs.
Logic bombs are a descendant
of those earlier Easter Eggs.
But logic bombs were designed
with malicious intent in mind.
Logic bombs are malicious code
that's inserted into a program,
and it will execute only
when certain conditions
have been met.
For example, a disgruntled employee
may insert a logic bomb
into the server's code
so that if that employee
isn't on the payroll anymore,
a bad action, like deleting
all the files, could occur.
One of my favorite
examples of a logic bomb
actually comes from the
movie Jurassic Park.
In the movie, the park's programmer,
Dennis Nedry, decides he's
going to put a logic bomb
into the power grid system,
so that it will go off at a certain time.
He does this so that when
the power gets turned off
by the logic bomb, he's able
to sneak out of the room,
go past all the alarms
and get into the nursery
and steal some of the dinosaur embryos.
He thinks he's going to get
off and sell those embryos
and become a millionaire.
Of course, it goes bad for him because
dinosaurs are running rampant in the park
because he turned off the electrical grid
and he doesn't make it.
But that's an example of a logic bomb.
He set it up so at a certain time,
a certain action would happen
and it had malicious intent.
Now, logic bombs and
Easter Eggs and backdoors
are all things that should not be found
inside our code.
These all go against our
secure coding standards
and best practices, so
you want to make sure
that none of this is
existing in your server code,
to make sure that you have the most secure
network that you can.