- In this section of the course,
we're going to talk
about securing your wired
and wireless networks.
We're going to start out
with wired network devices,
things like switches and routers,
and then we'll move into the cabling
that helps put all
these networks together.
After that, we're going to start talking
about wireless networks
and how we can better secure them
and all the different types of attacks
that exist for wireless networks.
We'll even go through a
demonstration in this section
where I'm going to show you how easy it is
to break wireless encryption
and we'll be able to do that
in about just two or three minutes.
So it's really important to understand
how to secure your networks properly
so attackers can't do this to you.
Now finally, we're going
to round out this section
by covering other types
of wireless technology
in addition to wifi,
things like RFID,
near-field communications,
bluetooth, satellite communication,
GPS, cellular, and others.
So let's get started.
(techno music)