- There are three basic
categories that you can use
when you're mitigating
threats: physical controls,
technical controls, and
administrative controls.
Physical controls are those things
that you add into the
real world environment
to stop things from happening.
This might be an alarm
system, a surveillance camera,
locks, fences, doors,
identification cards,
badges, security guards,
all those type of things.
For example, you can see
here there's a security guard
who's monitoring the
closed circuit television.
If someone tries to
sneak into the building,
they should be able to see it
and they can go take action on it.
This would be a great example
of a physical control.
The second type of control we have is
what's called a technical control.
This would be things like smart cards,
access control lists,
intrusion detection systems,
encryption, and network authentication.
We have lots of technical controls,
and we'll talk about them a
lot throughout this course.
The third bucket we have is
what's called administrative controls.
These are things like policies,
procedures, security awareness training,
contingency plans, and
disaster recovery plans.
Now, administrative controls
can further be broken down
into two categories, these
are procedural controls,
and legal or regulatory controls.
Procedural controls are those things
that your organization
chooses to do on its own.
Legal and regulatory
controls, on the other hand,
are ones that you have to do
because the law says you must.
For example, if you work
in the healthcare field,
you're going to have to follow HIPAA,
which is a regulation
and law that talks about
how you must secure the patients' data.
If you work in the
financial services industry,
you're going to be subject
to the Sarbanes-Oxley law,
which is a law here inside the
United States that discusses
how information must be
protected in that realm.
Now, we're going to go
into much more detail
into each of these areas
later on in the course.
For now, one thing I want to point out is
that user training, while it's
an administrative control,
is one of the most
cost-effective security controls
that you can utilize, because
at the end of the day,
no matter how many technical
controls you put in place,
you can have great firewalls,
an intrusion detection
systems, and encryption,
and all of these other things,
but if your user is going
to bypass all of those
by clicking on a link inside of an email
or sticking a thumb
drive into the computer,
it's going to go right through
all of your technical controls.
And so, you want to make sure
that you're using a good blend
of all three control types, physical,
technical, and administrative.
(quirky digital music)