- In this section of the course,
we're going to be discussing
monitoring and auditing.
Let's begin with monitoring first.
When we talk about monitoring,
one of the main jobs of security analyst,
is to really monitor the network.
We're like detectives, we're
trying to route out anything
that doesn't appear quite right.
And this can be done manually
or through an automated means.
When we do this to an automated means,
it's done through one of three methods.
It's either signature-based, anomaly-based
or behavior-based.
Now, when we talk about
signature-based monitoring,
this is where your network
traffic is analyzed
for predetermined attack patterns.
And so if I said,
every time you see somebody
walk through the door
who is five foot eight with brown hair
and whose name is Jason,
that's a signature.
So you would stop me at the door
because I met that criteria.
That's the idea with the
signature-based attack.
The second type is know as anomaly-based.
Now when we do anomaly-based monitoring,
we have to create a baseline
of what normal is first.
And once we established the baseline,
then we can look at any
other network traffic
that starts following
outside that baseline
for further evaluation.
So let's say you decided to
park your car on my street,
and you start watching all
the traffic that goes by,
and normally you see a lot
of people leave for work
between 7 a.m and 9 a.m
but, one time you saw
people not leave until noon.
You'd go, "hmm, that's
out of the ordinary."
Normally that person leaves
their house before nine,
and so that's outside the normal
and we're going to look into that further.
It's an anomaly, it's
outside of the baseline.
The third type we have is
what's known as behavior-based.
Behavior-based is an activity
that's going to be evaluated
based on previous behaviors
of the applications,
the executables and the
operating system in comparison
to the current activity of the system.
Now the problem with
behavior-based analysis
or behavior-based
monitoring is that it tends
to result in a lot of false positives
because there's a large
number of applications
and lots of different relationships
between those applications.
If you think about your computer,
how many different
applications are installed?
And how many ways do
they talk to each other?
You probably have Word,
and PowerPoint, and Excel
and Chrome, and Firefox and maybe Outlook.
And probably 50 or 60 other applications.
For you to be able to
create a good baseline
for all those applications
would take time.
And because that's usually not done well,
behavior-based tends to be
a lot of false positives
because people don't configure
it properly to begin with.
The one that has the least false positives
is signature-based.
Anomaly-based has a little bit more
and then behavior-based has a lot more.
So that's the three types
of methods we can use,
and these methods don't have
to be used in isolation.
Often times, in an intrusion detection
or intrusion prevention system,
we're actually going to combine
them into a hybrid approach.
So maybe I'm going to use
anomaly-based detection
and signature-based detection,
and that give me two different
ways of capturing traffic
for further analysis.
Now, that's the beginning of this section.
Now that we've got the
basics covered of monitoring,
let's dive a little bit
deeper in the next lesson.