- What is an IDS?
Well, an IDS stands for the
Intrusion Detection System.
This is a device or a piece of software
that's installed on a system or a network,
and it will analyze all of the
data that passes through it.
It does this so that it can try
to identify any incidents or attacks.
Intrusion Detection Systems
come in two different varieties,
the host-based Intrusion Detection System
and the network-based
Intrusion Detection System.
The first one we're going to talk about
is a host-based Intrusion
Detection System,
also called an H-I-D-S.
This usually takes the
form as a piece of software
that's installed on your computer
or on a server and it will protect it.
Now, the host-based
Intrusion Detection System
will sit there and log everything
that it thinks is suspicious.
We'll talk about what might be
suspicious in just a moment.
The second type is what's known
as a network-based
Intrusion Detection System,
or a NIDS, N-I-D-S.
This is a piece of hardware
that's installed on your network.
And all the traffic goes
through that switch,
and then it will get a
copy of that sent down
to the Network Intrusion Detection System.
If it's suspicious, it'll
log it and it'll alert on it.
Now, how do we know what
these systems will alert on?
Well, they're going to use one
of three different methods.
They're either going
to use signature-based,
policy-based, or anomaly-based detection.
Signature-based detection
is where the system
is looking for a specific string of bytes
that'll trigger the alert.
This works like any other
signature-based product.
This computer is going
to continually search
over and over for a known specific key.
And any time it sees that
combination of letters or bytes,
it knows that it's malicious.
It'll flag it and it will alert on it.
The next type is what's known
as policy-based detection.
This is going to rely on a
specific declaration
of the security policy.
For example, if your company has a policy
that no one is allowed to use Telnet,
any time this system sees somebody trying
to connect on port 23, which
is the port for Telnet,
it's going to flag it,
log it, and alert on it.
The third type is statistical
anomaly-based detection.
Often, this is referred to as just
anomaly-based detection or
statistical-based detection.
This is going to analyze all
of the current traffic patterns
against an established baseline,
and anytime it sees something that goes
outside the statistical norm,
it's going to alert on it.
So if I've been watching
your network for a while
and I know what normal looks like,
and everybody always works
from nine in the morning
until five in the afternoon,
and now I start seeing somebody
downloading large amounts of data
around two o'clock in the morning,
that's outside our normal baseline
and we would flag that and alert on that.
Now, speaking of alerts,
let's talk about what these alerts mean.
There are four different types of alerts.
They're either true
positive, true negative,
false positive, or false negative.
Now, a true positive means
something bad happened
and the system flagged
it and alerted on it.
That's good because it means
our system is tuned properly.
A true negative means something
good or normal happened
and the system didn't flag it.
Again, that's good,
because our system's
working like it should.
But when we get into something
like false positives,
this is where some legitimate activity
is being as identified as an attack.
For example, if you log on the computer
and you start up Microsoft
Word, that's authorized.
But if the system thought
that was malicious
and flagged it and alerted on it,
that's considered a false positive.
Now, next we have what's
called a false negative.
This is when something bad happens
but it's identified as
legitimate activity.
In other words, it isn't flagged
and it wasn't alerted on.
Let's say you downloaded a virus,
and you ran the virus and
something bad happened,
but your Intrusion Detection
System didn't see it,
didn't flag on it, and didn't alert on it.
This is a false negative.
So now that we have a better understanding
of true positive, true negative,
false positive, and false negative,
let's talk about what an
IDS can and can't do for us.
It's really important to realize that IDSs
are only going to alert and
log on suspicious activity,
they won't be able to stop it.
If you want the activity to be stopped,
then you need to invest in an IPS,
or an Intrusion Prevention System.
They work very similarly to an IDS
except they have the ability
to stop malicious activity
from being executed.
Now, IDSs and IPSs can create
a lot of valuable information for us,
and it all gets logged.
If you're using a host IDS though,
it's going to be logged to
your individual computer.
You want to ensure that
you set up a syslog server
and have those log files
routinely taken from the host
and send it to a centralized server.
Now, why would I want to do that?
Well, if someone's going
to compromise your machine,
we want to be able go back
and recreate through the logs
what happened to cause the attack
so we can stop it next time.
IF all the logs were kept on your machine
and the attacker got
access to your machine,
they could have damaged
or altered the logs.
But if we've been pushing
them off to a syslog server,
it means those logs are protected
from being modified by the attacker.
This is why we want to ensure we have
a good, pristine copy of our logs
so we can always go back
and protect our network
based on what we've
seen that was malicious.