- Security of Apps.
How do you know the app you
want to install is secure?
How do you know it's not
going to be spying on you?
How do you know there's
no malware embedded in it?
Well, you don't.
But the best way to ensure that you don't
get those type of things is
by installing applications
from the official mobile stores only.
If you're using an Android device,
that's the Google Play store.
If you're using an Iphone,
that's going to be the App Store.
Now, some people have taken their phones
and done what's called jail
breaking it or rooting it.
On an Apple device,
jail breaking it means
you're going to remove
the security protections
that Apple has put in place
so that you can take it
from your wireless carrier
to a different wireless carrier
or install third party apps
outside of the App Store.
As you can probably guess,
these are both bad security practices
and should not be done.
Now, we you have an Android device
we don't call jail breaking it,
we call it rooting it.
The reason is because Android is at heart
a Linux operating system.
So if you root the device,
you now have administrative
permissions over it.
And you can install whatever
applications you want
and make the phone do things
that it wasn't necessarily designed to do.
Again, making sure that
you don't jail break
or root your device is a good first step
to ensuring you have a secure device.
Next, you want to think about what browser
and what applications
you're actually running.
For example, if you're
using the Chrome browser,
that's a fairly secure web browser.
But if you decide to get
a third party web browser,
you don't know who it is
that put that out there
and if you can trust them.
Maybe they're giving you this web browser
but they're also taking a copy
of all your data going through it.
To avoid those type of issues,
always get official
applications when possible.
And speaking of web browsers,
one of the things you want to ensure
is whenever browsing the
web on your mobile device,
you're always going to the
secure version of a website.
That's denoted by the https at
the front of the web address.
This ensures that you
have a TLS tunnel created
between your phone and the server.
What's TLS?
Well, it's Transport Layer Security.
It's going to put a
encryption layer and a tunnel
between your device and the server
to ensure you have
confidentiality and nobody
is conducting a man in the
middle attack from you.
Now as businesses, we are
increasingly going mobile
all of the time.
An Enterprise Mobility
has a couple of things
that we need to think about
when we talk about
securing our apps as well.
One of those, is making
sure we have control
over those devices and
what apps are installed.
If your organization is going to be
providing the cellphone to its employees,
you have the right to install
mobile device management software.
MDM or Mobile Device Management
is a centralized software solution
that allows your system
administrators to create
and enforce policies across
all of the mobile devices.
This can ensure that
people don't install games
like Angry Birds or they
don't put a third party apps
or that they could only
go to certain websites.
Whatever precautions you want to enable
and whatever policies you want to enforce
is really up to your organization.
But in the end, it's the
thing that lets you do that.
Now, one of the things
that you want to consider
with your phones is they have
location access based on GPS.
Should you allow location
access to an application?
For example if you trying
to get use the Yelp app,
it needs to know your location
so it can make recommendations
of the restaurants around you.
Well, if you enable
location access to apps
and you're not sure who that app is,
that app can now track your
location and where you're going.
This is a privacy concern
and something you need to think about.
It's highly recommended that
you turn location services off
for any apps that you don't need it for.
Obviously, you're going to
need it for your GPS app
but for most other apps
you don't need GPS enabled.
So you can turn it off
for those particular apps
in your settings.
Another privacy concern
is the use of Geo tags.
What exactly is Geotagging?
Well, Geotagging is embedding
the geolocation coordinates
or GPS coordinates into a piece of data.
Most commonly, this is done
with a photo or a video.
By default on your Iphone
when you take a picture,
your GPS coordinates are embedded
into that photo as metadata.
That means wherever you post that photo
like on Facebook or Twitter or Flicker,
you could take that photo
and read those coordinates
and figure out where all
those photos were taken.
Now this is really handy if you went
and took a trip around the world
and want to figure out
which picture went with which location.
But, it does bring some
dangers to your organization.
For example, what if
every morning your manager
went to a local coffee shop
and they decide to take a picture
and post it on Facebook
everyday around 8am.
This would tell an
attacker that that manager
is not in the office everyday at 8am
instead they are at the coffee shop.
They can now target that manager
either at the coffee shop
or target that manager's office
because they know the
location of the manager
and where they won't be, in the office.
So, geotagging is something
that needs to be considered
when developing your
organization security policies.
It's up to your organization to decide
whether or not you want
to allow geotagging
but I highly recommend turning it off
for privacy and security concerns.
(instrumental music)