- In this section, we're
going to talk about
some of the different devices
that make up our networks
and some of the different attacks
that are used against them.
But before we do that,
we're going to cover quickly
the basics of the networks by
going through the OSI model.
Now in this section of the course,
we're going to do this as a quick review
because you should have already learned
the OSI model and the basics of networking
back when you studied Network
Plus, which is recommended
before you take the Security Plus exam.
Now if you haven't gone through
the Network Plus course already,
I highly recommend you go
back and review that content
before taking the Security Plus.
Whether you take the Network
Plus certification exam
or not, the information
contained in that curriculum
is really important to understand
so you can better understand the security
that we're talking about
throughout this course.
(digital buzzing)