- In this demonstration,
you're going to learn how
to create a VPN connection
from a Windows machine
in order to secure its
connection over a wired
or wireless network all the way back
to the corporate network.
Let's jump into the lab environment
and get started setting up our VPN.
In this demonstration,
I'm going to show you how
to create a VPN connection
on a Windows machine.
For this example, I'm going
to use a Windows 7 machine,
but it's pretty much the same process
in any version of Windows.
What we're going to do
is I'm going to click
on this wireless network
that's currently connected,
and I'm going to go to Open
Network and Sharing Center.
Now, from here, we're going to go
to Set up a new connection or network,
and this will bring up our dialog box
to create our VPN.
We want to use Connect to a workplace,
which is going to set up our
dial-up or VPN connection.
We'll hit Next, and then from here,
we're going to either
use it over the internet
or a direct dial.
In our case, we're going to
create a secure VPN tunnel
over the internet.
And then we'll give it our IP address,
in my case, it's 198.10.20.12.
And I'll give it a name, let's
call it the Corporate VPN.
And then from there,
we're going to hit Next.
We have to put in our
username and our password,
so let's say it was jason.dion
and my password of password
and then we can hit Connect.
And there you go,
you're now connected to the VPN
and you can see that we have an access
over a VPN connection,
and we have our wireless
connectivity on top of that.
And that's going to
make that secure tunnel
so that nobody can see anything
that we're transmitting
from our laptop over the internet
back into our VPN network.