- As we move through the seven phases
of the software development lifecycle,
it's important for not to forget
the fundamentals of good security.
Our developers should always remember
the three tenets of the CIA triad:
confidentiality, integrity,
and availability.
Remember, confidentiality ensures that
only authorized users can access the data
being processed by an application.
The most common of
ensuring confidentiality
is to include the use of encryption
to maintain the secrecy
of the data being stored.
Integrity is focused on ensuring the data
is not modified or altered
without permission.
The two main ways that
we do this as developers
is by utilizing hash algorithms
as a method of integrity
check for the data
or by using journaling
and logging functions
to create audit trail showing the
integrity of the data
has not been comprised.
When developers are attempting
to ensure availability,
they're focused on ensuring
that the data is available
to authorized users when it's needed.
The most common way of
doing this is by creating
redundancy in the overall system design,
by ensuring their software
code is error-free,
or by ensuring that their
software can conduct
error handling appropriately
to prevent crashes.
During the testing phase, it's important
to conduct an in-depth
code review to ensure
that there are no vulnerabilities
that might affect the
confidentiality, integrity,
or availability of the software
or the integrated system.
These code reviews are generally performed
by programmers, not by
security analysts though.
On the other hand, security analysts
do help during the software
development lifecycle
by conducting threat modeling.
Threat modeling helps to
prioritize vulnerability
identification and patching
throughout the SDLC.
By helping to prioritize the threats,
the security analysts can help with
the identification of
applications or systems
that should receive
additional protections,
which threats are more
likely to affect them,
and which ones have known
vulnerabilities that exist.
Based on this, additional
effort and funding
can be applied in the most efficient way
to fix the issues before an attack happens
or an attacker can exploit them.
After all, there are a
lot of threats out there
and a lot of ways to attack a system
if you want to breach an
area of the CIA triad.
To best protect applications,
we should ensure
that good security is programmed in
from the beginning back
during the requirements,
analysis, and implementation phases.
Numerous studies have proven
that it's much cheaper
to utilize secure coding practices
and to conduct more thorough testing
before releasing a product than to try
to fix insecure code after
releasing the product,
as well as trying to clean up
from the mess of an attack.
What secure coding practices
should our programmers
use during development?
First, we should ensure that
we design our applications
with the concept of least privilege.
Least privilege means
that user or processes
should be run using the
least amount of access
necessary to perform the given function.
Does your application require
administrative permissions to run?
If so, why?
Developers should always try to use
the lowest permission level
when they're performing a function.
So whenever it's possible,
the program should be run
as a user level person instead of an
administrator or root level one.
The next practice is to
implement defense in depth.
Defense in depth occurs when
you layer security controls
to create a more effective and
secure application or system
than would be possible if you
relied on a single control.
Also, you should never trust user input.
Any input that's received from a user
should always undergo input validation
prior to allowing an
application to use it.
Proper input validation can stop
a lot of different types of attack
including SQL injections,
buffer overflows, and more.
Next, we want to minimize
our attack surface
in our applications and our systems.
This means that we should always reduce
the amount of code used by program,
we should eliminate
unneeded functionality,
and we should also require authentication
prior to running any additional plugins.
Developers should also
create secure defaults.
Most of the time, our users are going
to accept the default
installation configurations.
This can lead to
insecurities in our systems.
Therefore, developers should always ensure
the default installation
includes secure configurations
by default and then requires
an administrator or a user
to lessen those secure defaults
if they want to remove the security.
Unfortunately though,
software is often designed
the exact opposite to this where they have
insecure defaults and then
it requires an administrator
or a user to change them
to add additional security.
Next, whenever you're
deploying your applications,
you should always use
code signing to ensure
that the program has not been changed
either inadvertently or maliciously prior
to it's delivery to your end users.
By using digital signatures
as part of your code singing,
you're enabling the end user to see
that the program was authentic
and it maintains the integrity
throughout its lifecycle.
Another key principle that
developers should follow
is to ensure their code is developed
so that it will fail securely.
After all, every application
is going to fail at some point.
By ensuring that your application is coded
to properly conduct error-free
handling exceptions,
they can fail securely instead of crashing
or being exploited by an attacker.
Again, input validation
here will go a long way
in helping your programs fail securely
instead of just crashing.
Next, we have fix security issues.
If the vulnerability is identified,
it should quickly be corrected and patched
to remove that vulnerability
from your application or system.
After all, we don't want
known vulnerabilities
to remain in our applications or systems
because when they do, this
means that vulnerability
can be found by an attacker as well.
Since we know about it,
they're going to be able to find it too.
Finally, developers should only rely
on trusted SDKs and third party libraries.
What's an SDK?
An SDK is a software development kit
and it allows a programmer to reuse code
from other programmers in order
to save them time and effort.
For example, if you're developing
a new Windows application
there's no reason for you
to code your own function
to open a file on the hard drive.
This function exists in almost
every program out there.
So, there's a software development toolkit
that provides this function
along with many other
file input and output functions.
The same holds true for
third party libraries.
We are reusing somebody else's code
inside your own applications.
Whenever you're utilizing
somebody else's code,
you should ensure it comes
from a trusted source
to ensure that no malicious
code is being added to it.
From my file opening example,
I would want to use the
official Windows SDK
or a third party library
and not some random one
that I found on SourceForge or GitHub.
(upbeat music)