- Vulnerability management.
A vulnerability assessment
seeks to identify issues
in a network, application,
database, or other IT systems
prior to it being
inadvertently or purposely used
to compromise a system.
Vulnerability assessments
are a formalized process
that define, identify, and
classify the security holes
in an enterprise network architecture.
It's also used to
forecast the effectiveness
of proposed countermeasures
as part of your overall
risk analysis process.
Now once these countermeasures
are put in place,
a follow-up vulnerability assessment
can help you to determine
how effective your
countermeasures truly are
in protecting that network from attack.
The management and
oversight of this process
is known as vulnerability management.
Vulnerability management is the practice
of finding and mitigating
the vulnerabilities
in your computers in your networks.
This is a very cyclical process.
Sometimes you'll hear this
referred to as scan, patch, scan
because you need to scan the network
for vulnerabilities to identify them,
then you're going to prioritize
all these vulnerabilities,
you're going to fix them and patch them,
and then you're going to scan again,
and you're going to keep doing this
until hopefully one day, you
have no vulnerabilities left.
Good luck with that.
It's never going to happen,
but that's the idea.
Now when you develop this
process within your organization,
you have to figure out what the goal
of your vulnerability
assessment is going to be
because this is going to help you design
a specific type of
vulnerability assessment
that you're going to utilize
and help you scope the overall assessment.
There are three main questions
that you need to think about
before you're going to design
a vulnerability assessment.
First, what is the
value of the information
that could be discovered
through the system compromise?
Second, what is the specific threat
that your system is facing?
And third, what mitigation
strategies could be deployed
to address the issues that are found?
Let's consider the first question.
What is the value of information
that could be discovered
through a compromise of the system?
This is going to help me
decide how much resources
and what kind of resources
I'm going to allocate
to identifying and fixing possible issues.
Let me give you a couple examples.
If you're a Coca-Cola
and you have a certain
file server in your network
that contains your proprietary formula
for the best soft drink ever made,
you'd want to dedicate a lot of resources
to protecting that server.
Now if you had another server
that had all of your public affairs,
things like your commercials
for the past 10 years,
you might not care about
protecting that nearly as much
because those are already
out in the public domain.
Next let's consider the
question of the specific threats
that are applicable to your system.
Each type of computer is
vulnerable to different attacks.
A Linux web server running Apache
has different vulnerabilities on it
than a Microsoft Windows-based web server
running Internet Information Services.
Both of these servers have
very different vulnerabilities
than a Cisco router or switch.
As you can see here,
the differences in their
operating system, configurations,
and operational use case
is going to make them prone
to different vulnerabilities,
and different threats
are going to attack them.
Now the final question is
what mitigation strategies
or security controls could we deploy
to address the issues that we find?
Well, let's look at another example.
If you decide to perform
a vulnerability scan
of every client on the network
and you found the same vulnerability
on every single client,
what mitigation strategy
could you use to fix it?
If it was me, I'd
probably want to make sure
that my patch server is working correctly,
and I'd want to make sure
that I'm pushing out a patch
to every client from this
centralized patch server
to make sure that everyone
gets the updated security fix.
Now what if there's no
patch available yet?
Well, then we have to look at the exploit
that the vulnerability is going after.
Let's say that this
vulnerability was being exploited
because somebody is going over Port 445,
what's that port again?
That's right.
It's the SMB service for file sharing.
Well, you could then mitigate this
by blocking that port at your
network boundary's firewall
as a compensating control.
It's still going to have a
vulnerability for people inside,
but you're going to stop the attackers
from the outside of getting in.
That's the idea here as
you start figuring out
how you're going to solve
your vulnerabilities.
Now the point is you're going
to have many different choices
for mitigation, but your
strategy is going to help you
determine how you're going
to solve these problems
because you only have different things.
If I'm more worried about inside threat,
stopping it at the network
firewall isn't going to help,
but if I'm worried about
outside threats, it would.
So by answering these three questions,
you're going to be able to better scope
your vulnerability assessments
to be more targeted
and better address the issues you identify
during your vulnerability assessments.
So how is a vulnerability
assessment even conducted?
Well, most commonly, a
vulnerability management program
will be used inside of an organization
and they'll choose what
software you're going to use.
Generally, the software
will be centrally managed
and perform these vulnerability
assessments and scans.
Common choices for scanning
include things like Nessus,
Qualysguard, and AlienVault software.
Luckily though, you
don't have to be familiar
with any of these tools in detail
for the Security+ Exam.
Now when you use these programs,
analysts are able to scan the
network based on the scope
and they can determine the priority
they're going to use
when they find issues,
such as missing patches
and misconfigurations.
These are then reported up
through the organizational process
to your system administrators
who will then patch and reconfigure them.
Once these are corrected
by the system admins,
you then want to go back
and re-scan the network
to determine if the issue
was really resolved.
Did that security patch
really patch the vulnerability
you thought it was going to?
It's important to note that
vulnerability assessments
are just a snapshot in time.
For example, if I scan today
and a new vulnerability
is discovered tomorrow,
then I'm not protected against
it, I never looked for it.
So if your organization
is doing a monthly scan
and a patch cycle that way,
your network may have an issue
that you're not even aware of
for up to an entire month
until the next scan.
And if the issue is identified
and the system administrator
installed the patch improperly,
it could take you another month
before it's discovered in
the next periodic scan.
So determining how frequently
you want to do these scans
is really important to your security.
Now to summarize the
vulnerability management process
in just five steps,
here's the basic concepts
you need to know.
Step one, define the
desired state of security.
Your organization should determine exactly
how safe it wants to be and
that determines how much money,
time and resources are going to be spent
to dedicate to the vulnerability
management program.
After all, you're not going to
be able to stop every threat
and you can't protect yourself
from everything equally.
Step two, create a baseline.
You need to understand what normal is
and what the current
state of your systems is.
Back in step one, we're going to
determine where we want to be,
what our goal is.
Here in step two, we need to determine
where we currently are
in terms of security.
This brings us to step three,
prioritize the vulnerabilities.
You might run your first
scan of the network
and find 150 different issues.
If you're the only security analyst,
which one should you fix first?
Well, this is why it's important
to prioritize your strategy.
I recommend fixing servers
first over work stations
and more critical issues
like a remote code execution
over more trivial vulnerability
like an ability to conduct
a null session connection.
This is because servers hold
lots of critical information,
and critical vulnerabilities
should always be addressed
before lower risk items.
Step four, you want to
mitigate vulnerabilities.
This is where you're
actually going to install
all those different controls,
install those patches,
do your change configurations
to make your systems more secure.
In step three, we prioritize,
in step four, we actually
put those things into place.
And that brings us to step five,
monitor the network and systems
and conduct future scans.
You now have a bunch of issues
you hopefully fixed or
mitigated all of those issues,
and now we want to watch and
ensure nothing bad happens.
Or maybe some of those things
are going to take months to fix
because you need more money
to buy a new server or
a new operating system.
If that's the case, you need
to monitor those servers
until you get them patched and fixed.
Your job is not done with just scanning.
You need to scan and follow through,
and then start scanning again.
Remember, scan, patch, scan
over and over and over again.
Our work is never done
because new vulnerabilities are
discovered every single day.
The good news about that
is it means you're going
to have great job security
because we always are going to have a job
for people doing vulnerability assessment.
(electronic music)