- OVAL.
The Open Vulnerability
and Assessment Language,
or OVAL as it's known, is a standard
that was designed to regulate the transfer
of secure public
information across networks
and the internet to
utilize any security tools
and services available at the time.
Now, what does this really
mean in layman's terms?
Well, OVAL is an attempt
to create a standard
way for vulnerability management software,
scanners and other tools
to share their data
with each other and with other programs.
Now, just like I can send you a photograph
saved as a JPEG file,
and pretty much every
program knows how to open it and display
that information
properly, because they all
understand what the
JPEG format looks like,
well, that's what OVAL does,
but for vulnerability
assessment information.
Now, OVAL is comprised
of two different parts.
There's a language component to it,
and an interpreter.
The OVAL Language is
written as an XML schema
that's used to define and
describe the information
that's being created by the OVAL Language,
and it's allowing it to be shared
among various programs and tools.
Now, the OVAL Interpreter
on the other hand
is a reference model that was developed
to make sure that the
information being passed
around by all of these programs,
it actually complies with the OVAL schemas
and definitions that the language created.
Because OVAL can be used
by lots of different tools,
it has become a large part
of vulnerability assessments,
patch management, auditing, the sharing
of threat indicators,
and multiple other uses.
Now, for the Security+ exam,
you just have to remember
that OVAL stands for
the Open Vulnerability
and Assessment Language,
and that it's used to
share data between lots
of different tools that are focused on
vulnerability assessments and management.
And if you do that, you're
going to do just fine.
(electronic buzzing)