- Now that we've dug into the concept
of risk a little bit more,
I think it's appropriate for us
to cover the concept of security controls
because that's exactly
what we're going to use
when we try to mitigate a particular risk.
Now, security controls
are first broken down
into three types, physical,
technical and administrative.
As you might guess,
physical controls are security measures
that are designed to deter or prevent
unauthorized access to
sensitive information
or the systems that contain it,
by preventing physical access.
So when we discussed physical security
earlier in this course,
we were focused on a
lot of physical controls
like fences and door locks
and alarm systems and security guards,
all of these things are focused
on protecting the physical
computers, servers and networks
from being accessed by people
outside our organization.
Our second type of security control
is called the technical control.
Technical controls are
safeguards and countermeasures.
They're used to avoid, detect,
counteract, and minimize
our security risks to our
systems and information.
So we talk about using passwords
and access controllers,
and encryption for our hard drives
and multi-factor authentication,
we're really talking about
technical controls here.
The third type of security control
is called an administrative control.
Administrative controls are focused
on changing the behavior of people
instead of removing the
actual risk involved.
So if I create a policy or procedure,
that states that every employee
has to lock their computer
whenever they're going to
be away from their desk,
this is an administrative control.
There's no technical
control being used here.
If you get up and walk away
and return within two minutes,
and you didn't lock your workstation,
there's no technical control
that's going to lock it for you.
I just made up a policy and
it's purely administrative.
Now, other examples of this include things
like mandatory vacations,
user education and training,
creating disaster recovery plans,
and implementing job rotation,
all of these are examples
of administrative controls.
Now, the National Institute
of Standards and Technology
or NIST, actually has
three other categories
that we organize Security
Controls in as well.
These are management controls,
operational controls
and technical controls.
Management controls are security controls
that are focused on decision-making
and the management of risk.
This usually includes things
like policies, procedures,
legal compliance,
software development
methodologies that you choose,
setting up a good vulnerability
management program,
and other things like that.
Management controls are all
about how your system security
is going to be managed and overseen.
Now, operational controls are focused
on things that are done by people.
With operational controls
I'm trying to increase
the security of the system,
by controlling the actions
of the individuals and
the groups who use it.
This includes user training,
configuration management,
testing our disaster recovery plans,
and conducting incident handling.
These controls are performed
by technical people
in order to carry out
the overall direction
that was provided by management controls.
The third category NIST uses,
is called technical controls.
These are logical controls that are put
into a system to help secure it.
This is things like triple A,
the authentication,
authorization and accounting,
access control, encryption
technology, passwords,
and configuring your security devices.
Anything that is technical
and performed by the computer
can really be put into this category.
So, now that we've covered
two different groups
of three categories each,
I bet you think we're done but
unfortunately, not quite yet.
We have yet another group of three,
that can be used to
describe security controls.
They are preventive,
detective, and corrective.
Preventative controls
are security controls
that are installed
before an event happens,
and they're designed to prevent
something from occurring.
For example, you might install
a technical control like a
RAID in your file server,
to ensure that your data
always has redundancy available
and prevent data loss from occurring.
Maybe you're worried about a power outage,
so you install battery backup or an UPS,
in order to prevent a brownout
or a blackout from happening
and causing your
workstation to lose power.
These are considered
preventative controls.
The second type of control is
called a detective control.
Detective controls are
used during an event
to find out whether or not
something bad may have happened.
If you have a closed-circuit TV system,
being monitored by a security guard,
this is a type of detective control.
Intrusion detection systems,
audit logs and alarms
are all different types of
detective controls as well,
when they have logging enabled.
Now, these aren't going to
stop a bad thing from happening
but they are going to
allow you to at least know
that it happened and follow up on it.
The third type of control is
called a corrective control.
Corrective controls are
used after an event occurs.
So, let's say somebody
hacks into your server
and they erase your hard drive,
well if this happens you're going to hope
you have a good backup copy somewhere.
If you've been doing good tape backups,
this is called a corrective control
because it's going to allow you
to recover from this data loss
and by fixing something after it happens,
it becomes a corrective control.
Other examples of this are found
as part of incident response
or disaster recovery,
or restoring technologies for data loss,
or replacing devices
that've been malfunctioned,
or switching your operations
to an alternate location,
to continue your business functions
in case there's a disaster and you need
a continuity of operations.
So you may be wondering,
can something be in one
or more categories?
Well, absolutely.
I've mentioned some of
them as we've gone through.
Consider the example of a
closed-circuit TV system,
if I have it installed it can
serve as a detective control
because I can see if
something's happening,
but it's also categorized
as a physical control
because it protects our physical devices
by allowing us to see people
as they approach the devices.
Similarly, if I have a password policy
created for my organization,
this isn't just a management control
but it's also an administrative
control because again,
policies fall into both those areas.
Now, I know we've covered a lot
of different controls so far
but I have just one more control to cover,
it's called a compensating control.
Now a compensating control is
used whenever you can't meet
the requirements for a normal control.
For example, let's say your organization
has a physical security policy
that states that every
door to a networking closet
or server room has to have a
retina scan enabled door lock,
to protect the devices in those rooms.
Well, maybe one of your
branch offices is located
in some far off country overseas,
and they have no retina
scan enabled door locks
being sold in that region.
Well, instead of using
a retina scan door lock,
you decide to install a cipher door lock.
The cipher lock will be
considered a compensating control
until you can get a retina
scan enabled door lock
ordered, shipped and
installed at this location.
Now, keep in mind that if you
use a compensating control,
you are putting in place a different thing
than the original requirement,
but you're still attempting
to get the same level
or close to the same level of security.
Any residual risk that is not covered
by the compensating control is considered
accepted risk by the organization
because this security
control doesn't fully cover
the same requirements as the
original control might've.
For the exam, I want you to
make sure you're prepared
to categorize things into these
different types of controls,
based on the ten types
of security controls
we covered in this lesson.
Keep in mind, some things can go
into multiple categories and that's okay,
that's why I presented these
things in the three groups
of three, and then the
compensating control.
(electronic music)