- There are a lot of ways to
store data in your network
and on your computers.
In addition to your internal hard drive,
most computers have the ability
to use removable media as well.
Removable media comes in
many different formats.
In the old days, we had
our simple floppy disks.
Then we moved up to CDs and then DVDs
and those held a lot more information.
Next, we had external hard
drives that plug in through USB.
And finally, we had USB thumb sticks
which are very small but
hold a ton of information.
When you're placing your information
onto one of these removable media formats
or external devices,
you have to make sure that it
stays safe from prying eyes.
We want to ensure confidentiality.
To do this, we always
want to encrypt our files.
You can do this in one of two ways.
On Windows 10, you can use BitLocker To Go
which will allow you to encrypt files
using a software encryption.
Also, you could buy a USB thumb stick
that already has hardware
encryption built-in,
something like an IronKey USB shown here.
Some organizations are a
little more paranoid though
and they want to ensure
that nothing gets out
of their organization.
And they also want to make sure
that nothing gets into their organization.
To do that, they've implemented
removable media controls.
These controls are technical limitations
that are placed on a system
in regards to the way
the USB storage devices
and other media can be accessed.
For example, this can be
done using technical controls
inside your group policies
by denying read access from USB drives
or denying write access to a CD or DVD.
In addition to these technical controls,
you also need to consider
which administrative controls
such as policies you want to create
and guide those technical
controls that are going to be used
inside your organization.
In addition to external
devices and removable media,
we also can store our data on our networks
and we might do something called a NAS.
If we use a NAS, that's a
Network Attached Storage device.
These storage devices connect directly
into your organization's network.
They often look like a
big rack of hard drives
with a network cable coming
out of the back of them.
Most of the time,
NAS systems are going to implement
some form of a RAID array
that gives you high availability.
Because these devices need
to be accessed at all times
because they're acting as file servers
for your organization,
this high availability is important.
Oftentimes, we'll take different NAS'
and we'll connect them together
into what's known as a
Storage Area Network or a SAN.
A SAN is a network designed
specifically to perform
block storage functions
and it may consist of many NAS
devices connected together.
Now if you're using a single NAS device
in your organization or at your home,
there are three tips I want to give you
to make sure that you secure it properly.
First, always use data encryption.
If your NAS supports full
disk data encryption,
you should turn it on and implement it.
Second, you should always
use proper authentication.
These things are acting as file servers.
You want to make sure that
it asks for credentials
such as a username and password
and that is individualized to each user
so no one is sharing access
across the organization.
The third thing is to make
sure you're logging access
to your NAS device.
This way if something goes wrong,
you can go back and figure out
who was the last person
who accessed the NAS?
Who downloaded those hundred
terabytes worth of files?
And what may have gone wrong?
These are important things
to know and without logs,
you won't be able to figure it out.