- As promised, here are my
top five tips for increasing
your score on the CompTIA
security plus exam and really any
CompTIA exam you take in the future.
Number one; use a cheat sheet.
Now I'm not talking about
writing it down on a piece
of paper and carrying
it into the test center
because you're not allowed
to carry anything into the
test center with you.
But they are going to give you
a a white board or dry erase
sheet that's the size
of about a normal piece
of printer paper.
Once the clock starts you're
allowed to brain dump stuff
onto that paper, things
like ports and terms and
anything else you might
forget by the time you get to
question 66 and beyond.
So while you know that
port 80 is http right now,
you might forget it somewhere
towards the end of the exam
when it's been about an hour, right.
You get fatigued and you
start forgetting things.
So I do recommend writing
things down like ports,
protocols, anything that you
might think you're going to
forget by the second half of the exam.
Using that cheat sheet is going
to be really helpful for you.
Second, skip the simulations.
Yes the simulations, or
performance based questions
as CompTIA calls it, are
usually the first three to five
questions on the exam.
Now these simulations actually
account for more points than
multiple choice so why am I
telling you to skip them first?
Well it's because most
students find these to be the
hardest questions on the
exam, so my recommendation is
when the exam starts simply
mark them for review,
skip them and do all of your
multiple choice items first.
I've seen students who will
spend an hour on those first
five simulations and then
run out of time for the
multiple choice and they fail the exam.
Instead I want you to go
through all the multiple choice
first and you'll still
probably have about 45 minutes
or 30 minutes left to do the simulations.
They don't take that long
but they are more difficult
and so by skipping them
you're going to gain a lot of
confidence going through those
multiple choice questions
first, and then when you get
to the simulations you're
actually going to remember
things from the multiple choice
that'll help you answer
some of those questions.
Third, take a guess.
When in doubt take a guess.
On the CompTIA security plus
and all of the CompTIA exams
there is no penalty for wrong
answers so when in doubt
try to eliminate as many
choices as possible and guess
between those remaining choices.
The multiple choice questions
only have four options
so you know that if you find
one or two of those that
aren't right, you're already
exponentially increasing
your chances of guessing the
correct answer out of the
remaining three or two
options that are left.
Now fourth, I want you to pick
the best time for the exam.
This is really important.
Are you a morning person
or a night person?
Pick the time of day
that works best for you.
You want to be awake, you want
to be alert and you want to
be well rested.
Don't try to squeeze the
exam in after working a long
day at the office.
Personally I like to schedule
my exams around 10am.
That way I don't have
to wake up super early,
I can avoid rush hour traffic
going to the testing center
and I can get there and just
kind of relax before I go
and take the exam.
Now when you schedule your
exam also make sure you allow
enough time to relax before the exam.
One of the things I do is I
show up about 30 minutes early.
There's nothing worse than
showing up at a testing center
at nine 59 when your exam
is scheduled to start at 10.
Instead show up 20 to 30 minutes earlier,
you can sit in your car for
a little bit and calm down.
You can go upstairs and use the restroom,
and then go check in for the exam.
This will help increase
your score, I promise you.
Now my final and fifth
tip is be confident.
You have got this.
You can do this.
When you walk into the
testing center, you shouldn't
be wondering if you're going
to pass, instead you should
already have studied all the
information in this course.
You've watched all the videos,
you've taken all the quizzes,
you've downloaded the study
guide, you've gone through it
and now you're going to go
take my practice exam right
after this video.
If you aren't confident right
now then you need to wait
to schedule your exam
until you've taken a bunch
of practice exams.
In this course I have a
full length practice exam
that's going to help you
determine if you're ready
for the exam.
Take that practice exam
and if you aren't scoring
high enough, restudy the
areas you missed and then take
it again.
Still not confident?
Go and find more practice
exams to take, either on this
site or from a text book or other sites.
Keep practicing these exams
until you feel confident
and ready to go and
then schedule the exam,
walk in there knowing
you're going to pass,
just like he did, and if
you follow my five tips
you're going to be ready to
take the security plus exam
and pass it on your first attempt.
Now, let's go ahead and get you certified.