- During an incident response,
we often need to collect
evidence of that cyber attack
for further analysis.
For example, if your main
server's been infected
with some kind of malware
as part of an attack,
you'd want to get that cleared up
and get that server back
online as quickly as possible
to minimize the disruption
to your operations.
But, if you do that, you may erase
the evidence of the attack,
and that would make it impossible
to figure out who did it.
Now to overcome this challenge,
we often use digital forensic
collection techniques
to make forensic images of
the data on those servers
and we use that as evidence
for later analysis.
By doing that, it allows
your incident response team
to help get your server back online
as quickly as possible
and resume operations,
but also maintain that evidence.
Now, your incident response
team may need that evidence
because they may be working
with law enforcement.
And if you're doing that, you're probably
trying to seek criminal prosecution
for the attacker who
broke into your systems.
Now as part of your data collection
and evidence collection efforts,
you're going to do a
lot of different things.
For example, you're
going to capture and hash
the system images.
This means you're going to
use a tool like FTK Imager
to make an exact copy of
that server's hard drive
and then hash it to make
sure it doesn't change
while you're analyzing it.
Then, you're going to analyze
the data you collected
using software tools.
You're going to use forensic tools,
things like FTK, the
Forensic Toolkit, or EnCase.
Then, you're going to have
to capture screenshots
of the machine.
What was the machine looking like
when you arrived on the scene?
You want to capture pictures of that
so you know exactly what it looked like.
You might go back and look at
your network traffic logs and captures
and go and review all that
and see how they moved
throughout the network
as you're trying to trace back the attack.
If you think somebody was
physically on your property,
you may want to capture video
from the closed circuit TV system.
As you're collecting all
this data and evidence,
you want to consider
the order of volatility,
which means which order does things
get modified by quickest?
The quickest thing that gets modified
is the cache inside the processor.
Then the memory, then the swap files,
then the hard drives, right?
And you think about which one
is going to get changed first.
When you do that you
have to collect things
based on that order as well.
And anything on the victim machine
can be modified if there's a
bad guy on that machine, right?
And so we want to collect the
evidence as quickly as possible.
Then, we want to take statements
from witnesses and administrators.
What did they see?
What made them think
there was an incident?
Maybe there was somebody who said,
hey, my computer all of a sudden,
the mouse started jumping
all over the screen.
That's something you need to
collect the information from
and figure out why it did that.
Then, we want to review our
licensing and documentation,
and figure out do we
have the proper license
for all of our systems?
And do we understand how they work,
and are they working the
way they were designed
based on the documentation?
And then of course we're
going to track our man hours
and our expenses, because at the end
of this incident response,
someone's going to say
how much did it cost us.
And if you look at most
data breeches in the U.S.,
large companies are suffering millions
and millions of dollars of losses
in the cost of these data breeches,
both in the response efforts to it
as well as the value of
the data that's lost.
Now, in the next lesson,
I'm going to show you
how a forensic disc
image is actually created
during an incident response.
For the security plus exam,
no one is going to ask you
to conduct this operation.
But, it's going to give you
a taste of digital forensics
and see if the idea of being a
digital forensics examiner interests you.
If it does, you may want
to download and play
with some forensic tools
like Forensic Toolkit,
I'm going to use in the
next lesson, or EnCase.
(upbeat music)