- Mobile devices are an
increasingly large part of our life.
They are doing everything
with us these days.
When we're on travel, we have 'em with us.
And sometimes if we're not
careful, someone can steal 'em.
For example, this guy's
about to get his iPad
stolen out of his backpack.
It's not going to be a
very good day for him.
Now, we have to think
about all of the data
that's on that device.
Let's say you were on a
family trip and you just took
a whole bunch of pictures
from your vacation.
And now you're returning
to the United States,
you're going through the airport,
and somebody steals your phone.
You're not just losing
the value of your phone,
but you're losing the value
of all of those memories
that may be irreplaceable.
So when you think about
what's on your device,
one of the most important things
is to always ensure that you
have a good device backup.
And the reason is, the
memories, the photos,
your files, that's irreplaceable.
The device itself, you may
have cell phone insurance for
or you'll just go buy a new one.
But the information on it
is what's really critical.
Now, let's take it to a darker side.
What else is on your device?
Well, if you're like most people,
you also do mobile banking on your device.
And so if you don't have your
device encrypted and locked
and protected, somebody
can take that device
and access your account.
That's another big issue.
So what do we do about this?
Well, the first thing is we
want to encrypt our device.
We want to use full disk
encryption on our cell phones
and our tablets.
By doing this, even if someone
is able to steal the device,
they won't be able to
access the information
on the device without the
proper PIN and encryption key.
Additionally, we want to make sure
that we're thinking about setting
up tracking on our device.
If the device is lost or stolen,
you should be able to be
pulling the information
from that phone and
where its GPS location is
to determine where it is.
Now, just because you know where it is,
doesn't mean you should
go get it yourself.
In fact, police recommend that you don't
try to recover your device
alone if it's stolen.
Instead, you should go to the police
and have them go with you to
the location of your device
that you've been able to find
based on its location tracking.
And how exactly can you find
out where your phone is?
Well, if you're using an Apple device,
you can use Find my iPhone.
If you're using Android,
you can use Find my Phone.
These are websites that
connect to your phone
based on its data location
and its GPS signal
and it will tell you where
that phone is located.
Now, these sites also have
some additional features.
One of them is the remote lock option.
This will allow you to
remotely lock you phone
from the website.
This will make it so it
requires a PIN or a password
before the person who has your device
can actually log in to it
and get access to your data.
Another great feature of
these sites is the ability
to conduct a remote wipe.
A remote wipe is going to allow you
to remotely erase the
contents of the device
to ensure that no information is recovered
by the thief.
Now, why would you want to
remotely wipe your device?
Because maybe you have some
personal things on that,
maybe you have personal text messages
or photographs or banking information
that you don't want anybody seeing.
By using remote wipe, even if the criminal
has your device, they're
not going to be able
to see anything on it
because you've already
formatted the device, even
from a remote location.