- How can we increase the
strength of our hashes,
especially when using them as
part of our password security?
First, we can use key stretching.
Key stretching is a technique
that's used to mitigate a weaker key
by increasing its effectiveness
and thereby increasing the
time needed to crack it.
When you stretch a weaker key,
the weaker key is run through an algorithm
to create a longer, more secure key
than is normally used.
And it has to be at least 128 bits long.
Many systems are going
to utilize key stretching
to increase the security they provide.
Systems like Wi-Fi Protected Access,
Wi-Fi Protected Access version
2, Pretty Good Privacy,
BeCrypt, and others
all use key stretching.
Another technique we can
use is known as salting.
Salting is a technique
of adding random data
into a one-way cryptographic hash
to help protect against
password cracking techniques
like dictionary attacks,
brute force attacks,
and rainbow tables.
Using a nonce is another method
to help secure a weaker password,
where a number used
once, known as a nonce,
is added to the
password-based authentication
to help prevent an attacker
from reusing your password
if they're able to steal it somehow.
Another good tip
to help prevent password
cracking attacks is
to limit the number of login attempts
that are allowed prior
to locking out the user.
Normally, you want this to
be set at three attempts,
so if they enter the password
incorrectly three times,
the account is going to be locked.
Yes, this can be a pain for the user.
But it does increase the security
and drastically slows down an attacker
who's trying to guess the user's password
and break into the system.
(techno music)