- DNS attacks.
There are four different DNS attacks
that you have to know for
the security plus exam.
There're DNS poisoning,
unauthorized zone transfers,
altered hosts files,
and domain name kiting.
Now, DNS poisoning occurs
when the name resolution
information is modified
in the DNS server's cache.
This modification of the data is done
to redirect client computers to fraudulent
or incorrect websites usually as part of
follow-on attacks.
The DNS system was designed without a lot
of security embedded into it originally.
This open architecture
assumed a level of trust
with all the other servers
which I already told you
is a pretty bad idea,
but that has been taken advantage of
by malicious attackers because
trusting is a bad idea.
Now, DNS poisoning usually occurs
on a company's internal DNS servers
instead of on public-facing DNS
servers around the internet.
With this type of attack,
the internal client
on the network has to make a request
to go to a website like diontraining.com
and whenever they make that request
the client first checks with their
local network's primary DNS server
to see if it knows the
IP address for that URL.
If someone has gone there recently
that IP address is
already going to be stored
in the local cache but
if the cache was poisoned
that user's now going to be redirected
to a malicious website
instead of the desired one.
To counter act DNS poisoning, secure DNS
also know as DNSSEC, has been created.
DNSSEC uses encrypted digital signatures
when passing DNS
information between servers
to help protect it from poisoning.
You can also prevent your DNS
servers from being poisoned
by insuring that you're
running the latest patches
and the latest updates to
make sure it's protected.
Our next type of DNS attack is called
an unauthorized zone transfer.
DNS servers are normally configured
to provide DNS data to a zone transfer
which replicates information
to other servers.
With an unauthorized transfer though
an attacker requests a copy of
that zone transfer information
and if they receive it
they now have a list
of all of your server
names and IP addresses
and this helps them
plan for future attacks.
Because of this, zone transfers should
always be restricted between two
known and trusted servers only
and not let other people
ask for zone transfers.
The third type of DNS attack is focused
on the client itself.
Every computer and workstation
has a file on it called the host file.
The host file is a plain text file
and it contains IP addresses and names.
This is a reference that
the operating system
is going to check every time
a DNS lookup is requested
prior to going to a DNS server.
So if the host file has a
domain name being requested,
it's simply going to provide
the host file version
of that DNS information
instead of going out
to a DNS server requesting it.
So for example, one day my son was not
doing his school work and
it was really upsetting me.
Instead I kept going up there
and seeing he was watching YouTube.
So, I logged into his
computer and I added the URL
for YouTube into his host
list and I pointed that
to the IP address for
his school's website.
Now, anytime my son typed in youtube.com
instead of getting the
DNS lookup for YouTube
and getting redirected to their server
he instead got the one from the host file
that I maliciously put in there
and it served up the
home page for his school.
Now, every time he tried to watch a video
he was told hey you got
to go to school, right?
I think this is pretty funny
and you may think it's funny too
but he was not very
happy about this change
and he couldn't for the life of him
figure out why YouTube
wouldn't come up on his laptop.
Now, I may have been a
malicious attacker here, right?
But I own the system so it's okay.
But if I was really doing this on
somebody else's computer
I could have changed
that host file to redirect it to a server
that I controlled, create a
website to look like YouTube
and then tricked them into logging in
and providing their
username and password to me.
To prevent your host file
from being manipulated
it should always be set to read only.
On your Windows machine,
your host file's located
in the systemroot\system32\drivers\etc
directory.
This brings up the concept of pharming,
which is essentially what
I was doing to my son.
Pharming occurs when an attacker redirects
one website's traffic to another website
that is bogus or malicious.
This is done by poisoning the DNS
or by modifying the host file on a system.
Anyway you do it, if
you're trying to redirect
somebody to another website
that's usually considered pharming.
Now our final attack is
called domain name kiting.
This attack exploits the
way that the registration
process works for a domain name.
Normally, you're given
a five-day grace period
when you're adding a domain name,
but if you delete it
before that five days is up
and you re-add it again,
the five days restarts.
So this lets an attacker
gobble up domain names
without ever having to pay for them.
And they can just keep
them in this limbo state.
This is more of an abuse of
the system than a real attack
but it does prevent a legitimate buyer
from obtaining that domain name
and so we do consider it an
attack in the security plus.