- In this section of the course,
we're going to talk
about malware infections,
because malware doesn't just
appear on your computer.
It doesn't just show up out of thin air.
Somebody has to deliver it somehow
and install it on your machine.
Malware can be delivered
in lots of different ways,
including through software,
messaging and media,
from a botnet or zombies.
It can have activate interception
that's going to put
malware into your network,
or it can have a privilege escalation.
Where somebody goes from being
a regular user to a super user
and infects your computer.
Also, there's back doors and logic bombs.
There is a lot of different ways
to get malicious software
onto your machine.
In fact, one of the
simplest delivery methods
is when somebody has physical
access to your machine
and plugs in something like a thumb drive
that's already infected.
So, when we think about malware
there's really two pieces of how
malware gets onto your machine.
The first, is what we
call a threat vector.
A threat vector is the
method used by an attacker
to access a victims machine.
Some examples of threat
vectors are unpatched software,
installation from a USB thumb
drive, a fishing campaign,
where one of your users clicks on a link
to install a program, and many other
different methods that are out there.
After we figure out what
the threat vector is
the next piece is what we
call the attack vector.
An attack vector is the
means by which the attacker
is going to gain access to that computer,
in order to affect you with malware.
Now I know these two
terms sound very similar,
but there is a key difference.
A threat vector is how we
get to the machine itself,
but the attack vector includes
both the way we got to the machine
and how we're going to infect it.
Let me provide you an example,
to hopefully simply
this just a little bit.
Let's pretend that your
house is a computer
and I have a cupcake that's
going to represent malware.
My job as the attacker
is to get the cupcake
from my house to your house
and put it on your kitchen table.
Now, that's my goal, as the attacker.
You are going to try
and defend against it.
The threat vector I use might be that
I can drive right up to your house,
because your house isn't
inside a gated community
and there's no security
guards looking for me.
This would be a threat vector,
your unguarded neighborhood.
Now if I walk up to your door,
and I start picking your lock,
and I enter your house,
and I place the cupcake
on your kitchen table,
this represents the attack vector.
It's all the things I did
from driving to your house,
to picking your lock,
and delivering that poison
cupcake onto your kitchen table.
That's the difference between
the threat vector and the attack vector.
Now, let's go back to the world
of computers for a moment.
Let's pretend that you
have an old computer
that's running Windows 7
and you haven't bothered
installing or downloading
the latest security patches,
because you've just been
busy and haven't had time.
Well, maybe you haven't
installed these patches,
in quite a long while.
So you have a computer that's
missing a critical patch,
like the Microsoft 17-010
patch, which came out in 2017.
This was an essential security patch
for the EternalBlue vulnerability,
this is a threat vector.
This is your unpatched computer,
but I don't yet have an
attack vector, not yet.
Now, as an attacker, I'm sitting there
and I'm scanning the internet.
I'm trying to find unpatched computers
and lo and behold I find your computer
and I determine that it's
missing this critical patch
and therefore, you're vulnerable
to an exploit against your
file and printer services,
which are known as SMB.
Once I run this exploit,
I'm going to be able to
gain access to your machine
and install some kind of malware on it.
This series of events now
becomes my attack vector.
In fact, this is the
exact same attack vector
that was used by the WannaCry ransomware.
What they ended up doing was
they searched the internet
for unpatched Windows machines,
and when they found them that
were missing the patch 17-010
they ran an exploit against them
to gain administrative rights
and encrypt the users files
and then post a message
saying, "Your computer's locked
and if you want to get the access to it,
you're going to pay me some money."
In this section, we're going to look at
various infection vectors
that malware uses.
As well as, how to prevent malware
from being installed on your system.
Also, we'll cover how to remove malware
if it does find it's way in.
So, let's get started.