- File systems and hard drives.
Another aspect of hardening
your operating system is
determining exactly what file
system it should utilize.
The level of security of your system
is effected by its file system type.
There are many different file systems
available to choose from.
We have things like NTFS, FAT32,
ext4, the Hierarchical File System Plus,
and the Apple File System.
Windows systems can utilize either
NTFS or FAT32 file systems.
It's highly recommended, though,
that you use the NTFS file system.
NTFS stands for the New
Technology File System,
and it's the default
file system format for
Windows because it's
more secure than FAT32.
It supports, logging, encryption,
larger partition sizes,
and larger file sizes than FAT32 does.
If your Windows system is running FAT32,
you can convert it to NTFS
without losing any data, though.
The easiest method to do this
is to open a command prompt,
and type convert, the drive letter,
and then /FS:NTFS and hit enter.
This technique is
something you should have
learned during your A+ studies.
If you're using a Linux system, you should
format the hard drive as ext4.
If you're using a MacOSX
system, you should use
Apple's File System, since it is the
newest, and most secure
one supported by Apple.
In addition to choosing the right type of
file system, as we just discussed,
it's also important to
use whole disc encryption.
This will help increase the
security of your system.
It's also important
for you to realize that
hard drives will eventually fail.
But there are five
things you can do to help
postpone that failure, and
ease your recovery from it.
First, you should remove
any temporary files
from your system by using
a disc cleanup utility.
Second, you should conduct
periodic file system checks.
If you're running Windows,
you can do this by
running Check Disc, and
the System File Checker.
If you're using Linux, you
should do a file system check
by typing fsck in the terminal.
If you're using OSX, you
can run first aid from
within the disc utility application.
The third thing you should do is perform a
disc drive defragmentation periodically.
On a Windows system, you can
use the defrag command from the
command line, or run the disc defragmenter
from within the graphical user interface.
The fourth thing you should do is ensure
you have a good backup of you're data.
After all, every hard
drive will fail one day,
so it's important to
have a good backup copy.
This can be performed using
different types of software or
cloud solutions, depending
on your business needs.
The fifth and final thing you
should do is ensure that you
understand how to use
different restoration
techniques and actually practice them.
This includes restoring
from a system restore point
within Windows, restoring a
system from a tape backup, or
backing up a hard drive, and even
restoring an individual
file from your backups.
After all, the only way
to truly verify that your
backup copy is good, is to
attempt a restore from it.
In one organization I consulted with,
they had years worth of backup tapes.
They spent countless hours and a lot of
money on this take back of system.
But, when they actually need
to restore from one of those
tape back ups, they weren't able to do it,
because the tape that
they needed was corrupted.
If they had practiced restoring
that data to a test server,
they would have known
earlier that that data wasn't
really there, and they didn't
have a good backup copy.
(techno music)