- In this demonstration
you're going to see
how a password-cracking tool
like John the Ripper is actually used.
Now, like most of the
demos in this course,
you don't need to know how
to actually use John the
Ripper to pass the exam
but this tool is heavily
used by security analysts
when performing vulnerability assessments
and penetration tests so I
thought I'd show it to you.
So let's use this tool as a
demonstration of the concept
of how easily and quickly
a weak password can
be broken using a tool like
John the Ripper or Cain and Abel.
Now, let's jump in the
lab and get started.
Now, to do this, we're going to try
to crack the password for
this Kali Linux machine.
Now I'll tell you right
now the password is toor,
which is a very standard
password that is used
by Kali Linux by default
when you install it
but we're going to go ahead through
the process of trying to crack that now.
So before we can try to crack those hashes
we have to gather those hashes
from the Kali Linux machine.
Now, by default, inside Kali Linux
these passwords are stored
inside the password file
and as a shadow inside the shadow file.
So we're going to grab both of those
and put those into a file
for us called my password
so we'll do that by typing
unshadow /etc/password
and then /etc/shadow and then
we'll pipe that over to
the file password.txt.
And it's done so now if I hit ls
you'll see that there is
the password.txt file.
So what does that password
file look like now?
Well, let's go ahead and
print it to the screen
so that you can see it.
And let's do more password.txt
and you'll see here you have
your usernames on the left
and then what group
they're associated with it
and how they're going to be logging on.
Now, under root you'll see that
long hash there at the top,
that $6$u all the way
through across the top,
that is the shadowed password,
the hash of it that we've captured.
Now, how do we crack that?
Well, that's where John the
Ripper's going to come in handy.
So let me go ahead and
clear my screen here
and what we're going to do
is type john password.txt
and hit Enter and John's
going to go through
and try to crack that password.
Now, it already says it found it.
It was very, very quick and
so to show that password,
we'll just type in john
-show and then the file
that we had used which was password.txt
and so you can see that
root was the username
and toor was the password.
You can see just how
quickly John can go through
and decrypt these hashes
back into something
that's usable for us
which is the password.
And now I could log
into the system as root
with password toor with no problem.
(logo buzzes)